He will be a staff for the righteous with which for them to stand and not to fall
and he will be the light of the nations and the hope of those whose hearts are troubled all who dwell on the earth will fall down and
Worship him and they will praise and bless and celebrate with song the Lord of spirits
First Enoch chapter 48 verses 4 through 5 the modern world doesn't acknowledge
but is nevertheless haunted by spirits, angels, demons, and saints in our
More time, many yearn to break free of the prison of a flat, secular materialism, to see
and to know reality as it truly is.
What is this spiritual reality like?
How do we engage with it well?
How do we permeate everyday life with spiritual presence?
Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen DeYoung host
this live Colin show focused on enchantment in creation.
The union of the seen and unseen as made by God.
and experienced by mankind throughout history. Welcome to the Lord of Spirits.
Well greetings Dragon Slayers and Giant Killers. I don't know why, but you're listening to the
146th episode of Lord of Spirits podcast. You don't know why they're listening or you don't know why
it's the 146th episode? I don't know why they're listening. I do know why it's 146. It's because
we've already done 145. And when you say you don't know why they're listening, are you just
acknowledging the vast variety of...
reasons, so you don't know anyone in particular, or are you saying you see no reason at all?
I see no reason for them to waste their lives on this program.
You're the guy who's supposed to do the self-promotion, man.
Never the less.
I'm trying to, you know, trying to balance it off a little bit, just a little bit.
Um, yeah, so, you know, that being said, I am Father Andrew Steven Damick, and I
I am ensconced in the palace of podcasting and the wilds of Raleigh, North Carolina.
And you are Father Stephen De Young, deep, deep in the fetted swamps of Lafayette.
Just me, not all the listeners who just heard that.
That's right. I'm just talking to you.
I'm not Spartacus, right? Like, we're not all Father Stephen De Young.
I think we should try that sometime, though.
I'd like all the callers to call in and introduce themselves as Father Stephen De Young.
I am Father Stephen De Young.
Well, we are live. We are taking callers.
dollars. So starting the second half, Mike walks
into a bar man again will be taking your calls and we're hoping that you call in with your
dreams. Hold on a second before we go any further. Yeah, this is a rare moment of sincerity, though
I'm also deliberately trying to anger a bunch of tedious people. Uh, memory eternal to Peter
Cullen. Yes, everyone. I just said memory eternal to a Roman Catholic deal with you.
Well, actually, I recently saw...
This will help make some more people mad because there's this idea out there
Since you brought it up father. Yeah, that there is some rule
Written somewhere saying yes, you may not say memory eternal about people who are not orthodox Christians
And I have never seen that rule written anywhere. I've never heard it from the mouth of any bishop
I've never seen that's all saying that's all saying they're tedious people. I know I know and that what I did see recently
Actually, and this is real. This is true. You can look this up on the interwebs
That there actually is a pastoral instruction from St. John Maximovich of Shanghai and San Francisco the great 20th century saint
In which he stipulated
How you can commemorate non-Orthodox people and he includes singing
Are you ready?
memory eternal
So someone didn't give him a copy of these rules either. It would say yes
So yes, if it makes you mad, I don't care stay mad
Yeah. Also, so memory eternal, Dolly Parton and
Tim Curry. Yeah. Well, but Peter, Peter Cullen is the one
that hurts the voice of your the voice of your the voice of
Optimus Prime Prime, everything. Yeah. I mean, he's got a heck of a
voice. God bless him. And yet it did a ton of other voices to I
mean, like, yeah, all kinds of stuff. But that's like, yep.
See, those of you who aren't gen X don't know, but
As we're getting old, our childhood is slowly dying.
That's right.
That's one of the many reasons
we're so bitter and grumpy and disaffected all the time.
I mean, that's a perfect segue for me
to quote Shakespeare here,
which I was already planning to do,
but I was not, I hadn't figured out how to get it in.
That you could consider yourself
Lord of infinite space?
If you, oh no.
That's king of infinite space.
King of infinite space.
Yes, no, no, you were talking about death.
you know, that sleep of death, what dreams may come when we have shuffled off this mortal
coil must give us give us pause. See, I was I was translating back from the Greek translation
of Shakespeare's works. Yes, that's right. Yeah, actually, it looks like some people
in the YouTube chat are just now receiving the news about the voice of Optimus Prime.
Oh, they didn't know about Peter Cullen. Well, sorry to have to let you know about that.
Yeah, yeah. That's a sympathetic voice, you know, like I
Like, I was tempted that re-releasing Transformers the Movie in theaters, but there's like no
way I'm going to publicly watch the scene where Optimus Prime dies.
Any time soon.
Would you blubber like a little girl?
I'm not saying I would.
Not saying I wouldn't.
People are going to start canvassing the theaters in Lafayette, Louisiana to see
see if they can catch you doing it.
Yeah, no, like, yeah, I'll, I'll admit, I'll admit, like, people may not know about this, but, uh, so after, um, why is his brain, his name gone for my brain, uh, Batman and Batman, the animated series, uh,
Alan West, no, not the anime, sorry, the animated series, that's the original Batman.
Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, uh, man, I'm off my game already.
My head
Who is like arguably the greatest Batman of all time?
Out of many Batman
Yes, but anyway
As opposed to the chat like right out it'll come to me when I'm not thinking about it, okay
See I'm an old man, but right after he passed away like they released a
DC animated movie of crisis on infinite Earths
which is like his last voice performance and it's like him doing Batman and Batman dies
in it and like gives his life. It's like, why are you doing that to people? Like that's
not just Jen Xers, that's millennials getting cut off at the knees.
Apparently Kevin Conroy.
Kevin Conroy. I had the Kevin and I couldn't remember his last name.
Yeah, I made it serious.
Kevin Conroy, like right after he passed away and they released that and it's just
like hearing him say.
you know yeah yeah well I mean I I all that being said I didn't hear a rumor
earlier this afternoon that this episode is brought to us by the fevered
dreams of AI that this episode is an AI hallucination is that true not real not
really okay this is however the Lord of Spirits episode in which AI was the
most involved.
So we just speculate as to what exactly that means now.
them. Okay. And and based on that subsequent experience, this is the most it will ever
be involved seems likely. So here's here's how I was involved in the production of this
episode. I typed into my browser which goes to Google on my phone. What should Lord of
spirits make an episode about, and the Google AI response was dreams.
after it scanned Reddit and stuff. That's it. That's all it was, but uh, so yeah, so that that,
but then, you know, so when I told you that, uh, you put into the same AI like, okay, they're
doing what about dreams? What should they do next? And it was the topics they gave after
it were just complete slop. Yeah. Just garbage remixes, just absolute junk. So it was
It's like, this is a one-off.
So if you're.
super hung up on AI, right? It is now useless to us, apparently, like this suggesting a
dreams episode is the most we will ever get out of an LLM. So well, have your least say
from AI from now on, have were people having dreams back in Genesis or in Chetlhoiak,
or, you know, some Doug McCleary, no, dreams started in the 19th century, I knew it with
Germans.
No, Germans go around stomping out people's hopes and dreams.
So 19th century Germans, sorry, German, German listeners, but I think the closest we have
right now, at least that has sounded off in the chat is we have one Danish listener,
which of course that is not Germany, but it is Germanic.
Well, but no, but if you're Germanic and not German, then the Germans keep trying
to take your country.
So.
That is true. Quite true. You know. Quite true. Speaking as a Dutchman, you know, we could take our verbal jabs here and there.
Okay guys, like you can, you're tough, you can handle it.
Yeah, so obviously dreams have been around as long as humans have.
And apparently dogs.
Something as round as along as dogs
well, no, well, I mean because
Dogs, I don't know if you know this but dogs very clearly have dreams
Sure sure sure it's certain certain dogs like right now. I'm in southern Louisiana. It is August
My mother is intelligent and so she's with the family in Minnesota
Right, so we've got her dog in addition to our dogs and her dog dreams all the time
Like anytime that dog is asleep she'll be like laying on her side and you see like her paws twitching
Like she's running and she makes little noises and stuff so
Yes, so technically I guess regardless of your your view of creation
Right like even if you're going for literal sixth 24-hour day dogs would have been created
earlier in the day than humans. Oh, that is true. Yeah. As land
animals. So that's why I say not only been around as long as
humans have been around a lot at least as long as dogs. And I
don't know, I'm sure someone will post somewhere about what
other animals dream like there's probably some kind of
bird or fish or something that dreams that was around the day
before or the period before.
or whatever you think.
And so somebody will post that, I'm sure,
be like, oh, I'm actually.
So the question is it so much like when did people
start having dreams?
So I don't know why you asked it.
But what do they mean, if anything,
what's going on when people have dreams?
And so this is one of those where
as much as I like to go back to the Chocolithic period and get into prehistory, we can't really
get into prehistory too much in terms of the human understanding of dreams because there's
kind of no way to get at that until we have language, written language, I mean, and texts
that we actually still have.
So, but we could say some things in terms of the ancient Near East, in terms of the earliest
layer of written history that we have and how they understood dreams.
And so as we've said on the show before, what we've commented on dreams sort of briefly,
We're seeing as a means of entrance into the
spiritual world. But we have to, and this is a little bit of review from what we've talked
about in the past, but we have to talk a little bit about what that means, right, because
a lot of people's view of what the spiritual world is, is kind of skewed.
Yeah, you might get this idea of like astral projection or yes being trend
transported to some other place dimension or realm or you know the
Astral Plane yeah some kind of the Astral Plane by the way is just the sphere
that the stars are in that's what astral means astral means stars man illusion
just but sorry old-time art Bell listeners that's the origin of the
were disaster by the way.
Which is something that is against the stars bad stars. Yeah, you've been dissed by the stars
I
Think the problem is not of our stars, but in ourselves personally nice. Thank you
So
That's not the way it was understood by ancient people. That's not the way the scriptures talk about it. That's not the way
The church has traditionally understood
The spiritual world
Um
And the ancient understanding and the church's understanding is more like that the spiritual
world is an overlay.
And the metaphor I have used for this in the past that is getting increasingly dated and
unwieldy and not understood by a lot of the audience is an overhead projector, which
a lot of you have never seen.
So, with transparencies, but...
But I'm working on cobbling together a new one based
on visual effects, because visual effects, digital effects
have layers.
That's true, CGI.
Like ogres and onions, right?
So look at it that way, right?
You have a layer which is a person in front of a green screen,
right?
And then you layer in things behind them, right?
And so
those what do they call the when you the the it's not Google glass anymore now
there's some other kind of like glasses that add you know enhancements to your
vision or whatever they add you know an overlay it's like oh yeah the whole AR
thing and yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah I'm sounding recently old I imagine like
there's just zoomers cringing left and right who are hearing this out there I
mean I don't have one of those sets of glasses but yeah I'm sure though we're
just like way out of.
like anyway. So it's okay. Old man yelling at cloud is the is the your final form. Yes. So
I am soon to achieve it. So I wish there were clouds right now here in southern Louisiana.
So it's not that there is this other place, this other realm, this other dimension of the
spirit. It's that
The spiritual world is overlaid over the material world that we interact with every day.
We just mostly don't see it.
And we've talked before on the show, we've done a couple of episodes talking about this
in detail that the noose is the faculty by which humans perceive it.
and how in the process of theosis, the process of salvation.
Our noose is purified to allow us to accurately see the spiritual world.
We've given the example of Elisha's servant who has his eyes open.
And so he sees the angelic host around him, right?
It's not that they suddenly show up around him.
It's just they were there and he couldn't see them, right?
So it's that idea.
And so the spiritual world and the material world are all part of the
same creation.
They're all together.
it's just we generally perceive and interact with it.
with the material rather than the spiritual, at least directly, but the material and spiritual
worlds as we've said before on the show are constantly interacting with each other, right?
So things we do in the material world in a completely material sense still have spiritual
effect and spiritual repercussions, right?
Yeah.
Easy example Christ says you give a glass of cool water in his name to a little one,
right?
is purely a, right, the water is material water right in the cup of a certain temperature,
one human giving it to another human, but there is immense spiritual significance and
significance in the spiritual world of that event, right? So things aren't isolated to
one or the other. There's a constant interplay between the two. And so when we say entrance
into the spiritual world, we don't mean that they thought that when you went to
sleep like your spirit left your body.
went to another place, right? Yeah, it's now you, you're, you know, the language is your
eyes being opened, you're seeing more of what there is. Right. Right. And so you are, because
your eyes are closed, you're not thinking with your conscious mind, right? Your news
interacting sort of directly with noetic beings and noetic reality.
Uh, the more that kind of idea and we've talked, I know that's that in and of itself is a weird concept if you've never heard as if this is your first episode. Sorry. Um, but we have, we have a couple of past episodes on the news or we go to that in like super detail.
But so what that means a little more concretely is that for ancient people, including the
ancient years...
this earliest layer, that meant that in dreams you would encounter God's spirits, demons,
right, agentic beings, beings with agency, right, beings who are not you, separate from you,
right, another thing, you would encounter them in dreams. And these would be beings that inhabit
The spirit
Now that includes, by the way, the ancient Near East, deceased humans.
Yeah.
Right.
So, in addition to encountering beings that we would categorize as noetic beings, you
would also encounter, right, departed human spirits potentially in dreams and their understanding.
Uh...
Now, make sure you're east as today, right?
Most dreams were generally for the vast majority of people perceived as being a passive thing,
right?
So it wasn't that you enter the spiritual world in the sense that like, you yourself
had some kind of new agency while you were asleep in that realm that you didn't have
while you were awake.
It was just, you were perceiving.
it and mentally interacting with it in a in a different way and so it was still
dreams are primarily seen as a passive experience you would you receive a dream
right a dream would be given to you right and this kind of understanding but
But there were then, as now, people who did lucid dreaming, either accident.
incidentally or on purpose and in the ancient world, those people who did the lucid dreaming
were most ended up being some kind of religious functionary in that that the fact that they
did that sort of made them qualified automatically to be some kind of profit or seer or other
function error. But that was...
than as now, sort of a minority of people.
So, as I just mentioned, the idea of dreams,
both receiving them and being able to sort of actively
deal with them was seen as part of the general phenomenon
of prophethood, of being a prophet, of prophecy.
And we also have an old past episode,
I think it's called profit motive.
profit motive, because that was super clever. If I do say so
myself, I think I came up with that. Maybe I didn't. I don't
know. Um, I'm taking credit for it now. This is Father Andrew
Erasure. It's a I think so. Yeah, well, yes, it happens. It
happens all the time. It's good for my humility, probably, but
not yours. Yeah. Yeah, I have a lost cause. So, uh, yeah,
So it's it's with
within, right, the receiving of dreams, the interpreting of dreams, the deliberate seeking
of dreams is a phenomenon within the overall phenomena of prophethood.
And it was seen in the ancient world though as a secondary tier of prophethood.
So the primary tier of prophethood, as we talked about in that episode, was...
Did the prophet was someone who had had a very direct
personal encounter
With a divine being right so obviously in the context of
Scripture that's with God
Right God of the Bible right the true God in the case of pagan prophets
that would be
some other spirit
right
deity in question that we would
see as be having been a demon
So that was that was the primary tier of
Prophecy, but and then
And that corresponded to vision so there's a difference between a vision and a dream
A vision
Is an encounter in which the person who has received
the vision is still active. So think of the book of Revelation, right? St. John is not,
it doesn't fall asleep and then sort of passively receive the contents of Revelation, right? He
is awake, he is in worship, and he enters into this vision and throughout the vision he's asking
questions. He's interacting with Christ, with angels, with different beings.
right? He's going to different places, right? So he is an active participant. You compare
that to even biblical cases that we're going to talk about in the second half of people receiving
dreams like within the dream, they're not active. They just, they're passive. They receive
the dream.
Yeah, serve observers.
Yeah. And so that primary tier of prophethood being about this kind of vision, direct
visionary encounter.
is why, as we mentioned in that episode, the earliest terms in Semitic languages for
prophets was not the words that now get translated, prophet, but the earliest here refer to them as seers.
Yeah, literally seers, people who see.
Because they have these visions. So dreams are secondary
Because of that because they're passive and also because dreams require
than this extra layer of interpretation, right? In a direct encounter, for example, again going
to St. John in the book of Revelation, no S, St. John will see something and he'll ask what is this
or what does this mean or when will this right and that gets explained to him, right? So that's
like included within the vision because he's an active participant.
whereas most other biblical examples of dreams, right, someone then has to come and interpret the
dream. Daniel and, you know, or Joseph, I mean, there's, yeah. Yeah. And so not just the receiving
of dreams, but the interpretation of dreams is also this role that the prophet plays.
Right. That's clearly not everybody can do it. And there's no like manuals. You just
look something up. Yeah. And someone being able to do it, as you see in a lot of the biblical
examples, someone being able to do it, marks them out as having this spiritual gift, right?
Yeah. Yeah. And so, yeah, so because of that, sorry, Peugeot, but in the Asia,
your ease. Wow. They didn't understand the second greatest Canadian there. French Canadian.
second greatest French Canadian. We got narrowed in, respect his heritage. But they didn't see
it in terms of symbolism in that sense you just described. There wasn't sort of a universal
vocabulary of dreams or of symbols within dreams, right?
somebody could just write a guide so that anybody could do it. The the
interpretation was seen as itself being a kind of visionary or prophetic act.
Rather than as a sort of scientific endeavor, right, where you're decoding it,
right? That wasn't how dreams were understood in the
You should hear East at least, right?
So, this interpretation of dreams is one type of divination.
We've talked about various types on the show at different times, like ecstasy, reading
entrails of sacrificial animals.
This one is Oneromancy.
Mmm. Oh narrow man say
There we go. Try that at your next party kids your next young adult guy. Oh narrow man see or no
No, no, try the word try on the word on the word
Promoting divination
And so yeah, so that and that is treating the interpretation of dreams
dreams as divination, right, as a way of foretelling the future in a way that allows
you to make wise decisions in the present, and you can probably think of some right
off the top of your head, some biblical examples of that, right.
And as we mentioned, right, we can only go back with dreams really and understanding
to the human writing, but we have examples of texts related to oneromancy.
interpretation of dreams. Going all the way back to the library at Mari. So we're talking
about circa 3000 BC. Where's Mari? In Mesopotamia. Mesopotamia. Yeah. So basically as far back
as we have written texts. So the earliest ones we have are about order romance. Right.
So this, so, uh, this points.
this being a very early phenomenon. Also, interestingly, this is one of relatively few places
where when you look at the earliest Egyptian texts and the earliest Mesopotamian texts,
they're virtually identical in terms of early like dream divination stuff.
Strongly suggesting common source or common experience or this is just growing out of the
same thing.
Yeah. Yeah. So that basically tells us that because those two civilizations by the time
they develop writing are still so similar that it's something that goes well back into
human prehistory. And prehistory just means there's no written records. That's what history
prehistory mean right that needs to be clarified prehistory the prehistoric does that
mean cavemen necessarily right before writing prehistory just means before
writing before we have any account any written account to go on so it was well
back into human into human prehistory and so within these texts there is a
distinction between and there's there's several distinctions we're gonna
make here along the way but this is the first one between induced and
spontaneous.
dreams. Spontaneous dreams are most of the dreams you've ever
had. Yeah, you go to sleep. You have you have a dream. And by
the way, kids, if you say, well, I don't dream, then that means
you are probably psychotic. What you just don't remember
them. You don't remember your dreams, right? Yeah, you got
a dream if you don't want to be utterly psychotic. Yes, don't
diagnose people with psychosis. I'm just saying we got some
those WebMD folks out there who are going to be like, ah, but yeah, yeah, you know, the
kind of dream, you know, spontaneous dreams is the dreams you just have when you're you're
going to sleep. I mean, this is what most of us have in these kinds of dreams. Right.
So the those are spontaneous dreams. But then there are induced dreams or voluntary
sleep.
right, which is much rarer. But in the case of the ancient Near East, what we're talking
about with this is not like, oh, I'm going to sleep. And I hope that I dream of my sweetheart.
Right. That's not what we mean. This is drinking stuff or hailing stuff, eating stuff and hailing
stuff, swallowing stuff that will knock you out and cause you to see stuff, right?
Drugs it's basically yes. It's nice. Yeah
That's a wacky tobacco. Yes. So this is that's what that is, right? And there's lots of examples of both, right? Very early on, humans figured out different ways to intoxicate themselves. And before that, they probably just hit their head against a rock a bunch of times. I don't know.
But, um, so...
that was a thing right and so but but in terms of oneromancy right that would be a way that someone
who was like okay I'm I'm seeking some bit of knowledge or wisdom or something about the future
from the gods okay you know come here drink this right they go on a trip right to then tell
I'll tell the religious functionary what they
saw right in their hallucination that gets interpreted to them and that's the information
they want it right so that's that's what we're on a very practical level that's what
we're talking about when we're talking about induced dreams so we're going to talk about
a couple of texts now from the ancient Near East that give examples of some of these things
first one is one that probably everybody listening to this at least has heard of
for sure.
And that's the Epic of Gilgamesh.
I don't know if everyone in the world has heard about it,
but if you're listening to this show, you probably have.
So the Epic of Gilgamesh,
we're not going to go into a whole bunch of detail about it.
Maybe we'll do an episode about it at some point.
There are sort of...
There's really a whole bunch of dreams in it,
but there are basically three headings,
headings, three sets of dreams that we could talk about.
the first one happens right away in the first tablet and that's Gilgamesh after
he gets thrown out of Uruk for trying to spend the wedding night with everybody's
wife that went over then about as well as it would go over now as a suggestion
from a government official right gets thrown out of town so he's all alone but
But he has a dream that he will find a friend.
He will find a...
Uh...
...
Close friend to accompany him, of course, if you know anything about the Epic of Gilgamesh that ends up being in Kee-Doo
and
That dream, but so he has the dream and then that dream is interpreted to him by his mother who by the way is a goddess
named Ninsun
So you see already with that first dream this idea that even Gilgamesh who we've been told is two-thirds divine
can't sort of interpret his own dreams even though that dream is a revelation from the spiritual
forces he requires an interpreter and that's you know a goddess who comes and interprets it for him.
So the second set of dreams these are good examples of induced dreams. So Gilgamesh and
and in Kidu are on their way to Lebanon.
literally in the story to the cedar forests of Lebanon and there they're going to face
the mighty humaba who is this giant monstrous creature and so while they're on the way
Gilgamesh is kind of trying to prep for the fight right and so every time they come upon a mountain
The Hy-
place. Gilgamesh goes up to the top and he offers sacrifices to Shemesh, the sun god.
And he drinks something involved with the sacrifice and asks for a dream. And in each case the
dream is very obviously bad. They're all about how terrible Humbaba is and how, you
know, who Bob is probably gonna kill Gilgamesh in the fight.
literally kill him, right? But interestingly in the narrative, you know, he, every time he has
one of these dreams and Ketu like spins it and Ketu's like, uh, Mick in his corner, right? You
know, he's like, no, you got this, man. You got it, bro. You could do it. You could do it and
sort of reinterprets whatever the dream was to be like, no, like seeing him eat the world means
that like you're going to win, you know.
So, uh, this is interesting for a couple of reasons, not just for that little bit of verisimilitude
of like your buddy trying to pump you up right before this fight.
But it shows how, um, number one, even though all those are bad, I mean, Humbaba ends up
getting killed, uh, and you'll get bashed in key.
to do actually win. So those kinds of omens and oracles and dreams are not, we're not
at least completely fatalistic, right? You could, you could reverse that somehow. And
you could kind of see this element of, you know, obviously interpreters can give you
different interpretations. And motivated people will probably give you positive interpretations
no matter what.
This will be important when we talk about some biblical examples, you know like
Why somebody would say no dream interpreter. I'm not telling you what my dream was you tell me what my dream was and then interpret it
Right, right because otherwise like oh, here's my dream. Oh, here's what you want to hear, right?
So
It's also a good example of right these induced dreams and then the third
third set of dreams, little darker, are a couple of dreams that Enkidu has later on
in the epic, where the first one, Enkidu has this dream where he enters into the Council
of the Gods, right? And this is a certain stage in the mess of the Potamene Pantheon,
So, Enlil is the big cheese, but Shamish is there and all these other...
Mesopotamian gods are there, and they're kind of arguing and deliberating. They've decided that because
because they killed the bull of heaven, either Gilgamesh or Enkidu has to die, one of the two,
and they're sort of arguing over which one. And because Gilgamesh is family,
Right?
Right.
largely. Everybody's leaning toward Enkidu, but then certain gods are trying to intercede
and be like, oh no, but Enkidu also did some good stuff too. But finally they decree the
ultimate result of this dream that Enkidu has is he becomes aware of the fact that the gods have
decreed that he's going to die beforehand. And then to sort of add insult to injury,
he has another dream and in that dream he sees like the horrors of
Shaol of the underworld of where he's headed and how terrible it is. Right. So then in the
story, he dies. Mesopotamian religion, not a super positive uplifting religion. No, kind
of about grim determination, like Dutch Calvinism, but he has, he has this.
these dreams, he ends up then dying and actually going into the
netherworld. And that's what within the epic, that's what
then causes Gilgamesh to freak out and decide that he needs to
become immortal because so that that won't happen to him.
Right. So the epic of Gilgamesh is not really a story
about character growth. Right. And so that's what he goes and
seeks out an epitome to try it.
alerted the secret of immortality. But there within in Qidu's dreams, you see a couple
of things you see specifically his his are not so much related to divination as they're
related to him entering the spiritual world him sort of directly seeing the albeit passively
seeing the the spiritual world around him right the state of the dead and
deliberations in the in the Council of the Gods right in his dreams so the
epic of Gilgamesh people have heard about probably read in some lit class and
college or something but maybe you didn't focus so much on dreams per se I
wager a lot fewer of you have heard of what's called popularly now the Assyrian
in Dreambook.
particularly by its Akkadian title, the Ishkar Zakhiku.
I think that, isn't that in the bookstacks at Walmart these days?
I think it's under a Syrian dream book, not under Ishkar Zakhiku.
It's actually more Zakhiku.
A little now in paperback. But, you know, you got to get the cue, you got to get the back of your throat.
Yeah, the cough.
Yeah. And so Ishkar means
basically book.
Zakiku is the Akkadian word for a spirit or a ghost.
And so someone might ask, so then why isn't it called the Assyrian ghost book, or the Assyrian
spirit book?
Well, Zakiku is not only the word for spirit or ghost, it's also the proper name of the
God of dreams.
Uh, second man, Morpheus is anyway, um, what if I told you, yeah, no, not that more, uh,
uh, the, uh, um, so yeah, so there is that, but there is, you can see just in that connection,
the fact that that is both the word for a ghost or spirit and the name of the
of dreams that there's this perceived connection between the world of spirits, the world of ghosts,
and dreams, right? Those are connected in terms of that worldview. And it dates from the Assyrian
period. That's why it's the Assyrian dream book instead of like the Babylonian dream book.
although most people think that
What's in the text wasn't original to the text that it's kind of a compilation
Because essentially what this book is and it's tablets, but
What this book is is sort of a a series of diagnoses and cures
It's like the DSM negative 14 I guess
for, specifically for dreams.
And so the diagnosis part is that there is a long list of different things you can dream
about and this isn't the same as the kind of symbolic approach I was saying they don't
take because it's not like okay so in your dream the man was wearing blue well blue represents
this and the fact that it was a man and not a woman represents that and da da da da is
about
.
more vague than that. Yeah, right. It's much more general. So here is an actual example.
This tells you again, something about a Syrian culture. If you don't already know, if you
had a dream about eating human flesh and who hasn't, but you know, if you have a dream
about eating human flesh, that means wealth is coming your way. Yeah. I mean, that's
This is an actual example.
Yeah, that's very, you know, it's very giant lore kind of stuff. Yes. So it's that kind
of thing, right? You dream about flying. That means this is going to happen. So it's very
much like omens. Yeah, right. The way they would look at like, Oh, you saw a raven, you
You know, a raven landed on your, your house top, that means this is going to happen, right?
So it's more in that Omen level, right, of understanding.
And so then that's sort of on the diagnosis side and then the cures part.
Now obviously, if you're dreaming about even eating human flesh, that's great because
now that means you've got wealth coming, right?
No problem there if you're an Assyrian, but if you have some other dream that means
something negative like something bad is going to happen to you.
family, like you're going to lose all your wealth, then you want to cure for that, right?
You want some procedure, something to do to prevent that from happening, right?
And so that's the cures part.
That's the make these sacrifices, do this ritual, yada, yada, yada, right?
And then, and then whatever it was that your dream prophesied would happen will not
actually take place, right?
So that's really the the contents. That's the contents of the text of the Assyrian dream book, but so there are a few interesting things
to say also within the book and its treatment
One of those is that
The Syrian dream book acknowledges three different types types of dreams
Okay, and so one of those is what we were talking about one type of dream is a message
From a God or a spirit or a demon or something right some kind of spiritual being is
Communicating something to you through a dream. Okay, so that's one category
Another category as we've already talked about is
Predictive dreams you have a dream. That's predicting something that's gonna happen in the future
Right so that you can either
Run towards it or avoid it, right?
But then the third category, I'll just say just in many cases though you
the prediction and trying to avoid it is what makes it happen. I mean, you know, if you find yourself
in a Greek play, for instance, yeah, well, irony is so ironic sometimes. Yes, exactly. So
but then the third type of dream is what we could call internal dreams, meaning
it acknowledges that some dreams are just something going on in your own head.
Yeah, or heart it's
It's not indicative of something else. Yeah
not saying it's important or that it's not real or that it's not spiritual it's
just it's just you it's just yeah it's not connected to the future it's not
connected to any spirit it's just something going on with you right but
that's important to note okay so because a lot of times this gets presented as
if like you know oh ancient people you know they thought dreams were these
mystical things all the time.
and you know now we know right no they acknowledge that a lot of maybe even
most dreams were just sort of internal you know you're worried about X and so
you had a dream about X you know like people in ancient times were just as
smart as people today huh what stopped them from having
microwaves in the ancient Near East was not that they were dumber than us. Right? Because
guess what? 99% of the people listening to this could not make a microwave. Okay? The
reason they could make microwaves in the ancient Near East is because a whole bunch of other
things had to be discovered and invented first before you could make a microwave.
And that hadn't happened yet. So, but they were just as smart, right? If they had,
If someone went back in time...
And explained it all to them. They could make microwaves right just as well as we can
So yeah, so they understood that right they understood that that's not like
Some new thing that's not a disenchantment or a you know demythologizing of the world like they understood that too
Where that other stuff comes in is when you deny the other
two categories, right? We'll talk more about that later, right? But they acknowledge that
there were some that were just sort of internal to the person. And another interest, this is
an interesting little note. I should, I should make Father Andrew read this so he could pronounce
all the Acadian words. I mean, all the Canadian Canadians, was that a Freudian slip?
the Akkadians can write in incorrect pronunciation.
Well, I don't know if you know this, but I live surrounded by Akkadians, Father Andrew.
Well there's Akkadians and then there's Akkadians.
This is Akkadiana.
Not to be confused with Akkad.
Yes.
But yeah, so one of the things you see in the Assyrian dream book is that there
There are, there's a.
So the enumeration of a bunch of different sort of religious functionaries who are involved
in dream interpretation and stuff within the Mesopotamian, you know, the mid first millennium
BC Mesopotamian world.
And it gives you the Katie names for that, and they kind of distinguished these as being
subtly different things.
So a she-ee-loo.
which literally means like a listener or an asker of questions, right? That was the
title for someone who specializes in interpreting dreams because the idea was
they would I guess actively listen to you recount your dreams. And then an
astrologer, somebody who was dealing with divination vis-a-vis the stars and
planets was a Tupasharu
a Mahuam, sorry, sorry, Pentecostals, you're going to get grumpy here, but there are religious
dictionaries called Mahuam who basically would use, you know, rhythmic drumming and
other techniques to place themselves in an ecstatic state in which they would make ecstatic
utterances.
You
Which would be interpreted as
Messages the spiritual messages the Toronto blessing as it were I
Didn't say that father Andrew said that
Not saying I don't agree with it, but I didn't say it technically let the record show
and
Then so the words Raki Mu and Raki to
Mu and two are the masculine and feminine endings. That's a prophet or a prophetess
A Beirut was a diviner and that's really in this case because we've had a bunch of different types of divination
That's really mostly a Haruspex
Haruspex is the Latin word that means somebody who reads the entrails
sacrificial animals and finally the Ashipu
was an exorcist ice and
So but as we say that right exorcism for a
Mesopotamian was a little different than Christian exorcism or Jewish exorcism before that for
that matter. Yeah, wasn't it more like bring in good spirits to drive out bad spirits bring
in good yes to drive out bad demons from my point of view. Yes, yes, or just get one
to buzz off. Right. It's right. Warding off different right and we've we've talked
about different especially in some of the Halloween episodes we talked about like
like Lill2 or Lilith, right some of the
these different they were considered demons the way we talk about demons even by ancient
people right yes spirit that did bad stuff you've got one of those hanging right somebody
curses you and six something on you and you want to get to leave leave you alone Zeus
thinks you're good looking you're desperate to get him to leave you alone yeah yeah right
Um, that's a little anachronistic because this is Mesopotamia, but, uh, it's
But the idea is this this person
Knows the rituals and stuff to do to get you get the spirits you want to buzz off to buzz off
And the ones you may want to invite to come around to come around
So that's a very different view even though we say oh, that's an exorcist
There's some clear dissimilarities to the Christian concept of exorcism from demons
But so what all that why did we go through all that well it shows you that even you know
By the first millennium BC
This is a highly formalized thing. This isn't just you know people around with theories. I think I figured out what dreams mean
Right, it's stuff like this, right or or somebody's pet
Projects or something there are within society
Functionaries and kings and rulers and go have people on
Effectively what we would call their staff in these different roles
who do these things for them, right? And we see that reflected here in the second half,
we're going to get into some biblical examples, but you see this reflected in some of the biblical
examples that there are people whose job is to interpret a king's dreams for him.
This was a sort of societal thing. Work if you can get it. I mean, yeah, you
be good at it because if you're gonna be near the king yeah
Well, also, so I mean, I guess the comparative thing in our modern culture is you know, everybody
probably has some place where they get their news.
I shudder to think what that is for most people today, but they have some place where
they get where they get their news that they have found to be reliable, right.
And so whatever that is has a role within a culture.
society group, right, of sort of providing news and stuff. This is the equivalent of that in the
ancient world, right? You want to find out what's going on in the spiritual world. What's, you know,
what's going on in the world, in the world as a whole. Well, you need some experts, right?
And some of those are dream interpreters. And so that's a thing in the ancient world. So
So, like I said, in the second half here, we're going to get into some biblical examples.
We're going to see how some of this stuff carries over or doesn't, the continuity and
discontinuities with dreams in the Bible.
All righty, well, you've wasted another perfectly good hour of your life listening to the
Lord of Spirits podcast.
We're going to be right back with the second half.
See you soon.
Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen DeYoung will be back in a moment
Let's take your calls on the next part of the Lord.
of Spirits. Give them a call at 855-237-2346. That's 855-AF radio.
To the modern mind, dragons and demons are just the inner demons of psychology.
And angels are often reducible to the better angels of our nature.
That is to our better human impulses and virtues.
Talk of spirits is really about psychology.
But to the ancient mind of millennia ago, even up to the pre-modern mind of just centuries ago,
these are real beings with personal presence
it our world and affect us.
Father Andrew provides a distillation and explanation of the material in the popular
podcast, The Lord of Spirits, which he co-hosts with Father Stephen DeYoung.
Get this brand new book today at store.ancientfaith.com.
That's store.ancientfaith.com.
We're back now with The Lord of Spirits, with Father Andrew Stephen DeYoung and Father
Stephen DeYoung.
If you have a question, call next.
Now at 855-237-2346, that's 855-AF radio.
They were back.
That was a pretty kind of meta ad.
I mean, it's an ad about a book, about the podcast, about, anyway.
John really missed an opportunity.
He really should have said before, the segue, see, it's the segues.
You guys need to work on the segues.
We should have done a take it away father.
Andrew before he's in the ad. Take it away. And then you should have at the end of your
bit gone back to you, John. It's a new era of radio, Father Stephen. We don't we don't
have to do that anymore. No, I see. I feel like the way you did it makes it seem all
too formal and impersonal. People want to feel like they're part of the ancient
faith family. Part of something. Yeah. Yeah, so.
Well, I don't I don't see any calls coming in yet. What's no wait wait. I'm receiving something not in a dream
Yes, we do in fact have a question coming in so
Mike DeGan just patch this person through as as I as I said, I think all of our callers should be Father Steven
The Young so welcome Laura Spears podcast
Hello
Not happening
There we go. Welcome. Welcome. Hi. Hi. This is Luke from Colorado. Um, and I, my question is, uh,
when our kids come to us, I have a four year old and a three year old, and they say,
I saw a demon in a dream, or I saw my patron saint in a dream. How should we react as
as though it's orchestration in a way that's not just materialistic.
skepticism, but it's not, I don't know, going off in a weird direction.
Yeah.
Not just patting them on their heads and saying, that's nice, or, you know, oh my gosh, quick,
get the priest.
Yeah, we're going to, so you're tracking with us, I'll just say that we are going
to be discussing some of this kind of thing because we're going to talk about the way
that this plays out in the Bible.
But I mean, the short version I would say
is that the biggest question is what the child does with that not you know what is the because
like you didn't experience the dream right not what is the what is the phenomenon happening
here but rather how should we understand and respond to what we're experiencing right
so you know if someone says that they see a demon then you can talk okay what are
demons, you know, and the fact that we're
Protected from them by our baptism by our prayers by our repentance by our patron saints, you know, or if they
They're dreaming about their patron saint or you know something much more beautiful and good
Then talk about okay, so what you know, what happened and and
What what do we know about your patron saint? You know and all that kind of stuff?
I'm maybe a three or four-year-old it would be a little bit harder to to do that
You know, but I think that the key thing of course is you know
if they're frightened to talk to them about the protection of
God and the fact that you're there for them and and so forth. And if they're not frightened
and just to talk about the same, you know, the kind of stuff that you would normally
do as a parent, you know, your instincts are probably pretty good for a lot of that kind
of stuff. I don't Father, what would you have to add?
So I have a great nephew who see that great really.
I think so.
Okay.
And size-wise, he definitely...
is. Uh, he's one of you Dutch people. Yes, he's inherited the, uh, who, uh, a few years
ago when he was around that age, like matter of fact, Lee informed his parents one morning
that he had gotten up to go to the bathroom, saw a ghost, grabbed an icon and charged at
it and it disappeared. I mean, he went back to bed.
checks out. Yeah. So I think that is the correct course of action.
Um, but so, yeah, I mean, I, I think, I mean, I really just doubling down on what Father
Andrew said.
I mean, I think there's a knee jerk reaction to just be like, okay, dreams aren't real.
It's not, you know, um, don't pay any attention to it.
And I mean, if nothing else, there are things in life that we have to confront that scare
us.
right and
The way we deal with that is not by denying they exist at least that's not a healthy way of dealing with them
So yeah, I think it's rather interesting, you know you want to raise
Dragonslayers not people who don't believe in dragons. That's right. That's right. I
Hope that's helpful. Does that fill in some blanks for you?
Yes
They seem to be taking the more negative side, like Father Steven's great nephew.
So I'll take that conclusion.
Awesome.
Thank you, Father.
Rock on.
Okay.
Thanks for calling.
We're going to take another call.
We have a phone call from James from Jackson, Tennessee.
James.
Welcome to the Spirit's Podcast.
Hey, Father.
Hey.
Sorry.
I'm really awkward.
I'm really awkward on the phone.
It's okay.
I was calling because I was curious.
Okay, I was calling because I was curious
about something. And I think he just talked about the last call I just talked about like
what was it like how do how do you guys sort of like deal with let's say
because I don't know if this is just me or if other people have had these experiences.
I've had dreams of a sort of a spiritual nature that involves certain things that I think Father
Sarah from Rose talked about and
his books, specifically regarding like extraterrestrial beings, et cetera. And they didn't really,
they didn't make me feel like a sense of dread or anything. But they were very strange to
say the least. And I talked to my spiritual father about this, Father Matthew and St. Nicholas
Orthodox Church. Shout out to St. Nicholas. It's a great community.
Yeah. Um, I don't know. I just, I guess I kind of wanted to touch on like how you guys deal with,
you know, let's say whenever somebody comes by and they maybe have these sorts of strange
spiritual dreams. I don't know. I think the previous I wasn't listening because I was waiting on
on the call but and also how do we like
Oh, it's a difficult question to ask. Can I start over? Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. So I guess the question is, how do we as orthodox Christians really approach these profound, mystical, spiritual dreams some of us may have in a healthy way, how do we
like go about, you know, figuring out, are these from God? And how do we apply them in
our lives in a way that is healthy? Yeah. And also, what are your thoughts? Talking about
the nature of the dreams that I had? What are your thoughts on sort of this extra
terrestrial stuff that's been kind of talked about, especially more recent.
Now that all this stuff's been coming out with like with the government, how do y'all like approach that stuff, or do you not even touch it with a 10 foot pole?
Oh man. See, people keep wanting us to do UFO episodes, Father Stephen, but
So, so I mean, what do you do with all that stuff?
Well, we know what the goal is as Christians, right? The goal is to become faithful to the
commandments of Christ so that
we can become more like him, right? That's what repentance consists of, is increasing our faithfulness
and turning away from unfaithfulness. So, you know, is this from the Lord? Is this from some other
source? On some level, right? Like especially if you listen to this podcast for a long time,
on some level it kind of doesn't matter because we know that even demonic activity is something
That God
God uses, it's definitely something God permits and the reason He permits it is for our repentance.
So He may permit a demon to tempt us and to send us thoughts in our sleep in order to
be the basis of repentance for us or He may send an angel or a saint or direct himself
Or, you know, when you're waking, he might send someone to you to say something to you, right?
It's all from the Lord, if we use it as from the Lord, right?
If we repent with it.
The way that we get off kilter is if we act in ways that are not faithful to the commandments.
Right?
Absolutely.
Yeah.
So if someone thinks, oh, I had a dream, and that means I need to start doing something
really unusual, well, number one, you need to discuss that with your father, confessor.
You know, or like you might say, well, I received a message in my dream and I need to go around telling everybody in my parish that they're that they're big sinners, and I have the answer for their lives, right?
Which, you know, is definitely a thing that happens in some kinds of churches.
You know like that's that's that is a thing that people do. Well, that's you know
Unless you're their priest or their bishop and actually see that there is some kind of malignant
sin that's afflicting the whole congregation, then that's actually not your job. And so if
you start doing that, then what you're doing is not from the Lord, you know.
Yeah, you're being a ranting madman. Right, right, or just or an arrogant jerk,
or a know-it-all who's interested in everybody else's sins and not in your own. I mean there's
all kinds of possibilities as to where it could go. So the question is what you do
with it right that's that's really the
the question. So yeah. And I would say, you know, even whatever phenomena you might experience
from whatever source, the question is what you do. I mean, this is something I've said
a bunch of times, because we live in an era in which, in many cases, a lot of hidden things
are being revealed that are very upsetting and should be very upsetting, terrible, terrible
things people are doing. On the other hand, it's like, well, human beings have always
done terrible, terrible things. And that doesn't mean
of course, that we should be just comfortable with that. But what it does mean is that the
mission of the Christian has always been within the same context of dark conspiracies in the
world doing terrible things. So that means the mission of the Christian is the same.
You know? Yeah. Father Stephen DeYoung talked about that on his interview with
Tucker Carlson, you know, finding out all the stuff in the news. It's like, well,
been like this for a good few thousand years now so I've heard that
up and arms about it now yeah so yeah I don't know father you have anything you
want to you want to add on to that or yeah I mean this is just related yeah I
mean a lot of these things you judge by their fruit right like you know you have
some dream that causes you to quote-unquote realize that everyone
who disagrees with you just doesn't realize your spiritual greatness.
That's no good for you or anybody. Right? Like there's a word for that. There's a word
for that. Yeah, that's right. Those kind of things. And so that word, that's my new favorite
word coming to orthodoxy. Oh, look at it. And you can tell us that a lot myself. Yeah.
And so you look at a big problem with that myself. You look at something like that.
You say, well, I don't see any way where this could generate anything good. So you
to say well
forget it. That was, you know, shouldn't eaten that Brussels sprout burrito right before
going to bed. But Brussels sprout burritos now. Yeah. Anyway, right. But that bit of
beef, right? But you know, if but if it's something, you know, you also don't have
to do. There's this weird like over-analysis, right?
You know if you have a dream and you see
somebody who in the dream who you loved and you care about who's recently departed and the dream brings you some kind of
Comfort or soulless or positive feeling you could just stop there man like
Yeah
It's just be okay. Thank God. That was nice
right you don't have to you don't have to
to beat around the hole is
Is it real?
Am I being deceived?
You know, you can just...
Good fruit, right?
Just let it be.
You know?
You don't have to overanalyze everything.
Right?
Yes, we're prone to.
But now, in closing, I have a question for you, sir.
Oh, boy.
Oh, yeah, sure.
When you're on your way home, when you're on your way home, do you listen to I'm
going to Jackson or would your wife get mad?
Well, I'm single.
I'm the only one.
Oh, okay.
Thank you.
And I kind of just scream at traffic in my car.
I don't really listen to much on the way home.
Well, maybe you suggest something on the way home.
Yes.
Allow me to suggest Johnny Cash as a more wholesome alternative
to Rotary.
Amen.
Ah, yes.
Yes, indeed.
Hey, but I will say this.
Talking about the fruit, when I had this dream,
I didn't think less of anybody.
And what it did tell me was that no matter what,
you think is going to happen with aliens or the government.
or lizard people or Nephilim or whatever that Christ is king and that, you know, he is our Lord and our Savior and he loves us deeply and nothing can harm us in any meaningful way so long as we're united with him.
And I think everybody should go with that. That's my that's my opinion.
Absolutely. We know how this story turns out in the end.
Yeah, yeah. Oh, it's Dumbledore. Oh, wait
Thanks for calling James in wrong story. Sorry wrong story. All right. We're gonna take one more caller and
We have Trish calling from the old North State the land of the longleaf pine
North Carolina Trish. I was worried for me. There was my wife calling it to be mad at me different
I can be mad at you. Would you like for me to be mad?
up. No, I have enough of that. It might be a nice change. I have mad at me at home. No,
she would just be mildly irritated that I brought up the Brussels sprout burrito.
So that yeah. Oh, fortunately, the first caller had the same question I did as far as
are the dreams coming from your angel or a demon? And should we listen to them if
we can gain knowledge from it. Also what about premonition dreams? Because I've had lots of those.
Stuff you dreamed about and then it happened?
Yes, not that, not things that I would work towards making it happen. And I wouldn't even realize
like I wouldn't even remember the dream until I was literally involved in the exact same situation.
like I was a social worker and I had a dream about being in a school and um a tornado coming.
Well 10 years later I was teaching in a school and we were having a tornado and you know I got
the kids into the hall and we started praying and it went over us um it missed the school completely
but then I had remembered oh my you know I had this dream like 10 years ago so things like that
like places that I would
Be
Years later. I'm in that exact place like a place that I'd never been before and it's like oh my goodness
This was my dream. Like I'm in this exact. I don't know
That's the thing that happened
Yeah, it is. I mean it is the thing that happens
What do you think?
If it happens to you a bunch and if it happens to lots
of other people. Is it weird? Okay, but it could be weird in that Anglo-Saxon
which means sort of fade. Yeah. Well, right. No, but I mean, I mean, that's
so there's there's lots of things that we think are weird, but we think they're
weird because they don't conform to a particular scientific materialist view of
the world that we were indoctrinating when we were growing up, right?
But that that's just weird from that particular perspective, right. So I'm an orthodox priest.
An icon occasionally just giving forth vast amounts of olive oil.
Is not weird.
If you're an orthodox priest.
It's a thing that happens.
Okay.
Right.
So, brought that side to it.
materialist perspective, that's weird, right, or another example. Long, long before I knew
my wife when I was still young and foolish, and lacking in guidance, foolish now. Yes,
I was seeing a different woman and I gave her some holy
water from theophany, right? And she's like, well, what do you do with this? I said, well,
you just, you know, if you start feeling sick or something, drink a little bit of it. And
like a year later, she told me, you know, this last year, every time I started feeling
sick, I drank some of that. And I never really got sick this last year. Isn't that
weird? It was like, well, no, that's not actually weird.
Right that's normal. All right, holy water contributing to your health is normal
So, yeah, I think I think part of what we've been doing on the show since the beginning is trying to redefine weird
For one perspective we talk about all the weird stuff about Christianity
But part of the goal is this stuff shouldn't be as weird as we think it is relics shouldn't be weird
to you, right? These things shouldn't be weird. So we need
to normalize some of these things again, and make some
certain other things weird. Right? Like having a materials
worldview is weird. Having a knee jerk denial of anything
miraculous and wonderful is weird. Right? Those are the
things we should think are weird. Self destructive behavior
is weird, i.e. sin, right?
Yeah
What do you think Trish? Does that kind of inch you towards?
Maybe seeing these things it's less weird or something helpful at least at the very least
Yeah, absolutely, but you know that it's more normal than
one would
Think or that we work hot to think put it that way. Yeah, I mean I the problem comes right like like, you know
What you told Mike, our screener was, you know, should you trust your dreams, right?
Right.
You know, trust them to what purpose, right, for what, you know, the question is, again,
what do you do with it?
What do you do with this?
Right.
Do you, am I, am I repenting with it, am I, you know, being following commandments
of Christ, am I being kind to others, am I, you know, sacrificing my own comforts
for other p-
people's welfare, that kind of stuff. So whereas if you, if you decide your dream means
X and you trust that and you act on that, but it's harmful to other people, then no, you
should not have done that right now. Absolutely. Yeah. Yeah. So I mean, I think that the
fact that maybe you're feeling deja vu rather than actually remembering all the permanent
premonitory. Yeah, Seattle, that's not what I need. I need very often, you know, things you
you dream about beforehand. It's probably useful that you don't remember that. That way
you don't go around thinking, I know what's going to happen. You know, better, better not
to function in that way. I think so. Yeah. Okay. Anyway, well, thanks for calling. Nice
to hear from somebody else. We're in North Carolina. Well, I'm on the crystal coast,
it wasn't very crystalline today. Oh well. Yeah, anyway.
Well, all right. All right. Thank you guys. You too. All right. Here we are in the second half.
Let's talk about dreams in the Bible. So what's with dreams in the Bible?
There are dreams in the Bible. That's right. Bible dream. Yeah. So
and there's there's I mean there's there's some examples that if we talk about dreams in the
Bible and dream interpretation. We know and we're going to touch on those brief.
the ones that automatically just jumped into your head when we said that right? Yeah. But we also
and we're actually spent a little more time on maybe some of the ones that maybe you didn't notice
maybe you passed over a little quickly and so and a lot of this is showing you know we went over
to the first half, the sort of the general ancient Near Eastern milieu.
and its view of dreams, and a lot of that, there's a lot of continuity, broad continuity,
right, details obviously are going to be different, but broad continuity in a lot of areas with
the way the scriptures talk about dreams. That in itself may, you know, you may have
been listening to the first half going like, oh yeah, those weird pagans thought this
dah-dah-dah-dah.
But I'm...
Obviously, you know, the Bible doesn't, you know, take dreams that way.
Well, you might be a little surprised at how much continuity there is.
And so the first major point of continuity is that some of the earliest references we
have to dreams and dreaming in the scriptures are directly connecting the idea of dreams
to prophecy, and that starts.
in the Torah. Yeah. Yeah. So numbers 12, 6. I'm about to make Father Andrew do a lot of
reading. Yeah, it's okay. That's what I'm an excellent reader. Numbers 12, 6. And he said,
hear my words. If there is a prophet among you, I the Lord make myself known to him in
a vision. I speak with him in a dream. And then if you keep reading the next verse
basically says, not like how I
appear directly to Moses. So this is like, I'll talk to you, you know, to prophets in
dreams. Moses I talked to face to face, but other people's can be dreams.
So it's still within the context of the prophetic phenomenon, as we saw here, yeah, in the
ancient areas broadly. But also it has that sort of secondary status, right? Moses had
this direct face-to-face interaction with God. Dream.
Dreams to communicate is this second tier, right? Yeah, like we talked about
And that continues
Okay, so next in the tour passage. We're gonna read from is Deuteronomy 13
Verses 1 through 5
If a prophet or a dreamer of dreams
Arises among you and gives you a sign or a wonder and the sign or wonder that he tells you comes to pass
And if he says let us go after other gods, which you have not known and let us serve them you should not
listen to the words of that prophet or that dreamer of dreams for the Lord your God is
testing you to know whether you love the Lord your God with all your heart and with
all your soul. You shall walk after the Lord your God and fear him and keep his commandments
and obey his voice and you shall serve him and hold fast to him. But that prophet or
that dreamer of dreams shall be put to death because he is taught rebellion against
the Lord your God who brought you out of the land of Egypt and redeemed you out
of the house of slavery to make you leave the way in which the Lord your God commanded
you to walk, so you shall purge the evil from your midst.
It's got to be careful if you guys set yourself up as a prophet or someone speaks on behalf
of God.
Yes, yes, but also notice, right?
And people are probably familiar with this passage in terms of prophets and false prophets,
right?
But they may not have noticed ever that prophet here is paralleled with dreamer of dreams.
Yeah.
Right.
That those are presented as being almost synonymous here
Yeah, and that isn't just something, right?
So the Torah originates with Moses in the late Bronze Age.
This isn't something that gets left behind, right?
So we can go to the other end of Israel's history to right before the exile of Judah,
right?
So we're moving forward, again, I don't care about the date of the Exodus, somewhere
between 700 and 1,000 years.
right to to a much later period but that connection still holds right there isn't some sort of
refinement in profits you get this at a lot of I don't know if it's still as popular as it used to be
because it got associated with a lot of boomer lib stuff but they're sort of dying out of
of scholarship and everything else, but this idea that these these
Classical prophets that sort of Isaiah Jeremiah Ezekiel that that this
Again everything evolved right so like that's sort of the the the sort of full blossoming
blossoming of the prophetic tradition as if it's now this
Phenomenon that started primitively with Moses and I was blossomed into its fullest form
term, but you find the exact same kind of language.
being used, especially related to the relationship of dreams, right, in Jeremiah at this much
century, century, centuries later. And now in the axial age, right?
Yeah.
Yeah. All right. So Jeremiah chapter 23, starting with verse 25, for I have heard what the prophets
have said who prophesy lies in my name saying, I have dreamed, I have dreamed. How long
shall there be lies in the heart of the...
prophets who prophesied lies, and who prophesied the deceit of their own heart, who think to
make my people forget my name by their dreams that they tell one another, even as their fathers
forgot my name for bail.
But the prophet who has a dream, tell the dream, but let him who has my word speak my
word faithfully.
What has straw in common with wheat, declares the Lord.
Does not my word like fire, declares the Lord, and like a hammer that breaks the
rock in pieces?
For behold, I am against the prophets, declares the Lord, who s-
steal my words from one another. Behold, I am against the prophets to clear the Lord who
use their tongues and declare declares the Lord. Behold, I am against those who prophesy
lying dreams declares the Lord and you tell them and lead my people astray by their lies
and their recklessness when I did not send them or charge them. So they do not profit
this people at all declares the Lord.
So even in this late fully developed stage of profit hood.
The prophets are claiming that they received their revelation from God
Through dreams
Right through dreams that they give and then interpret
right
And there are a couple other places in Jeremiah
That we can read real quickly that do basically the same thing
Yes
So Jeremiah 27 9 just one
here. So do not listen to your prophets, your diviners, your dreamers, your
fortress tellers, or your sorcerers who are saying to you, you shall not serve the
king of Babylon. And then Jeremiah 298. For this says the Lord of hosts, the God
of Israel, do not let your prophets and your diviners who are among you deceive
you and do not listen to the dreams that they dream. Definitely get the
sense that not everybody who says, hey, I'm receiving something
here.
there should be this is too. Yes, right. That's yeah. Yeah. But so this will say and so now
you may think okay, yeah, cool Old Testament prophets, right? But you know, you haven't
listened to our prophet motive episodes. So you think, or you haven't read the book
of Acts carefully. And so you think that prophecy just sort of ends with St. John
the forerunner there are yeah yeah there's no more for panic activity
But lest you think so
right yes
In St. Peter's sermon
On the day of Pentecost and acts to verse 17
He quotes Joel to verse 28 and says
Actually, it's verse. Yeah. Yeah, 28. So he has exactly exactly. Sorry. I'm looking at the numbers. I'm like wait 28 17
What are we doing? Take it away father at 2 17
I didn't know that.
days it shall be after I made that big boast about being a good reader here I'm
stammering and in the last days it shall be God declares that I will pour out my
spirit on all flesh and your sons and your daughters shall prophesy and your
young men shall see visions and your old men shall dream dreams and so say
Peter is saying that's fulfilled on the day of Pentecost yeah it's happening
now meaning that the dreaming of dreams
We'll be available to everyone because of the presence of the Holy Spirit. Yeah. Yep, not that it's going to end
It's gonna be fulfilled not by being abolished because those are not the same thing
It's gonna be fulfilled by this being
able to everyone
And we see that
This was a standard way
This was considered to be a standard way that God communicated with people, not just with
prophets, right, but a way in which God would answer people.
And one of the places we see that in the Old Testament, that again, we may have missed,
this is a story most people are familiar with, and that we've talked about on the
show before in other contexts, right, famously Saul, sort of the last great evil
thing that Saul, King Saul, not Saul of Tarsus.
King Saul for the tribe of Benjamin in the Old Testament. I guess Saul of Tarsus was with the tribe of Benjamin too. Anyway, King Saul Old Testament
For seven sort of the last great wicked thing that he does
I mean he messes up a bunch of times, but
is going to the witch of Endor to summon up the spirit of the prophet Samuel, right and
Obviously bad thing to do and this gets talked about in a lot of other contexts
But if you haven't read closely, you might not know exactly what it was that motivated
him to do that.
But if you read a couple of verses in chapter 28 of 1st Samuel or 1st Kingdoms, you know
it.
Yeah.
So verse 6 says, And when Saul inquired of the Lord, the Lord did not answer him either
either by dreams, or by urim, or by prophets.
And then verse 15. This is this is after he has successfully gotten this is actual necromancy
by the way boys and girls have successfully gotten the witch of Endor to call up Samuel.
It says then Samuel said to Saul, why have you disturbed me by bringing me up?
So I mean, that way. Yeah, it's got to be, you know, I mean, come on. It's got to be that way.
I made the Dickens reference and here we go. Okay, go ahead.
these are the chains that's all answered I am in great distress for the Philistines are
worrying against me and God has turned away from me and answers me no more either by profits
or by dreams therefore I have summoned you to tell me what I shall do yeah right yeah
So, is that what motivates him is?
But he is desperate to get a response from God about the future, right?
About what he needs to do in terms of making war with the Philistines.
And despite his prayers, God isn't answering him.
But we get that list in the first verse you read of the three ways in which God would
normally answer the king.
And the first one listed is by dreams.
Yeah.
And then secondly, the Urum, meaning the Urum in the Thummim, which were cast sort of as
lots from the High Priest's garment.
They're not stones you put into a hat and then put your face in the hat and get medical
translations.
No.
And you won't find water that way either.
Or by prophets.
Prophets is listed third.
And so I did it.
And again, as Father Andrew read so dramatically, when he's answering Samuel, he says, God
had turned from him and answered him no more, either by prophets or by dreams, meaning previously
he had.
Yeah, I mean, isn't this after the Holy Spirit left him?
Yes.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Seriously, God had answered his prayers in some cases.
through dreams but that now had stopped and so he was desperate before going into
battle to get a word from God and that was being denied to him and so he resorts
to divination which is explicitly what the Torah said you should not resort to
right yeah right so clearly the significance of dreams their
relationship to prophecy. As we saw there with Saul, dreams is
means of communication from God to humans, right? In this case, the true God to humans.
These are these areas of continuity. But another area of continuity that you see, especially
not exclusively, but especially in the wisdom literature in the Old Testament is that the
scriptures also understand a lot of dreams as just being what we called internal.
Yeah.
There's things going on within the person. Not every dream is a communication from God.
Right. Right. Not every dream is prophetic in some way. Yeah. Right. Not every dream is revealing the
future in some way. A lot of them, maybe most of them are just internal. And so we've got a bunch
of examples here that Father Andrew is going to read, got to put them to work, but the
These are all short examples, but that talk about dreams is something ephemeral, right?
Yeah.
Something you wake up and it's gone, right, something in the van.
And that's talking about these internal dreams, right?
They don't have any greater significance than whatever is going on within a person,
right?
Yeah.
Okay.
So, Job chapter 20 verse 8, He will fly away like a dream and not be found.
He will be chased away like a vision of the night.
So.
You wake up, you forgot.
Psalm 7320, like a dream when one awakes, O Lord, when you rouse yourself, you despise
them as phantoms, basically the same kind of idea.
Psalm 90 verse 5, you sweep them away as with a flood, they're like a dream, like grass
that is renewed in the morning.
Ecclesiastes 5, 3, for a dream comes with much busyness and a fool's voice with
many words.
And then Isaiah 29, verses seven and eight and the multitude.
of all the nations that fight against Ariel, all that fight against her in her stronghold
and distress her shall be like a dream, a vision of the night, as when a hungry man dreams
and behold when a thirsty man dreams and behold he is drinking and awakes faint with
his thirst not quenched, so shall the multitude of all the nations be that fight against
Mount Zion.
And then finally Isaiah chapter 56 verse 10, his watchmen are blind, they are all
without knowledge. They are all silent dogs. They cannot bark, dreaming, lying down.
loving to slumber. Is that about dogs dreaming or? It seems like it might be.
It could be. Could be. Interesting. So, but yeah, you see it. So, again, within the scriptures,
it's not saying, right, every dream is a profound spiritual vision, right? Yeah. A lot of them,
maybe most of them probably most of them because we don't remember most of them.
They aren't any great revelation of anything about the future about the you know from God
Even about ourselves really right. It's you know
What I don't know. Have you it so I?
This is personally directed to father and so I
Used to my my stress dream used to be the recurring stress dream for a long time because I spent
I've spent way too much of my life in graduate school. It was always
it's the last day of class. I was enrolled in a class and didn't
know it. Now I have to do like the paper and everything and
try to get all the work done in some insanely short amount of
time so I don't fail. Right. That has changed. That has
changed over the last maybe 10 years. Now my stress dream is
the bishop is here at the church and I can't find my vestments and liturgy is
starting yeah so I don't know have you experienced something similar yeah yes I
would say since we're getting personal now I would say for for a long time I
I mean, I still, I'm gonna say that there's overlap
between these, right?
But,
For a long time, my my stress dream was
There's something it's similar to your your first one there's something that I'm
Overlooking something that I'm missing and it's going to ruin everything
Something I don't know, you know, I haven't thought of everything
right and then and then I would say that
Maybe and more and this probably just reflects, you know, my current life experience
the stress ones I have now are about
Something hurting my kids.
something is going to, terrible is going to happen to them. You know? Yeah. Yeah. So you took it to
a depressing place, but I don't know. I'm going to try and recover this segment and we recover the
segment. But my point being that, right, like, what's that about? What is the big, well, the big
revelation is I've lived my whole life based on overconfidence and under preparedness. And so
So there's always in the back of my head the idea that someday that will catch up with
me.
right. So that's what both of those dreams have in common. There's no greater significance
than that. It's just this nagging reminder to me that like, Hey, yeah, you've skated
by so far, but eventually, right? You're going to, you know, the chickens will come
home to roost, right? Um, you know, so you don't have to go much further than that.
So that when we're talking about it in terms of
eternal dream, right? That's the kind of thing we're talking about. Right? It's based on
and even, you know, Father Andrews, right? Obviously, as a father, he's worried about
his kids, right? Like, and so when he goes to sleep, him being worried about the well-being
of his kids manifests as, you know, that kind of dream, right? There doesn't have
to be any greater, doesn't necessarily mean it's a premonition that something is
going to happen and to write any of that.
it's just an expression of concern. So it's something that's going on in your conscious mind at some
level during the day. You go to sleep and, oh look, there it is in your dream too, right?
Yeah. So that's just an example of an internal dream. There's also very clearly,
we mentioned one example of this already, but I know I've talked about this.
before, but it may have been in the Bible. Who knows? I talk too much. I never remember
where I said what, but no one has time to listen to everything I say, like for Pete's sake.
Did you know that there are people who have listened to every episode of this podcast
multiple times? Yeah, but they haven't listened to every episode of this and every episode
of whole counsel of God multiple times and all the other lateral
stuff I do multiple times that it's not humanly possible if there is someone out
there like that I don't think that we want to meet you know I don't want to
know like get help get help it's just a TV show yes but anyway at some point or
other somewhere. I talked about the idea that contains
in Scripture within Genesis as a pattern and then within the Hebrew Bible or the Old Testament
as a whole, there is this theme, and we already gave one example with Moses versus the later
prophets, that dreams are sort of this secondary means of communication as opposed to the sort
direct communication that God has and so an example of that
is God of course starting in right away at the beginning of Genesis chapter 12
appears to Abraham yeah and talks directly to Abraham Abraham is his
direct encounter with God Isaac also when you get to Jacob you have this
weird mix, where sometimes he has
direct encounters with God and like wrestles with him right and other times
like in Genesis 28 verse 10 right he this is 28 verse 10 he has he goes to
sleep and has the vision of the ladder or the ziggurat or the staircase or
right the stairway to heaven depending on how you want to translate that right
But that comes to him in a dream
have both with him. During Abraham's life, while Abraham is having God appear to him directly,
Abimelech on the other hand, who is one of the people who Abraham lied to about Sarah
being his wife, because he was scared that his wife in her 80s and 90s, I mean, so
well preserved yes with the hell in me
of the ancient world was so attractive that, you know, someone was going to murder him to
take her, but so he's one of the people he lied to. And a bimilek, God comes to a bimilek
not in person but in a dream and tells him not only like, hey, that's actually his wife,
tells him I prevented you from doing anything with her that's why you're
going to die, which of course makes a biblack very upset at Abraham like you lied to nearly
got me killed. Right. Hey, whoa. Yeah. That is pretty cool. Your aim. So, yeah, so there's
this pattern with Abraham of Abraham. It's a direct relationship. Somebody like a biblack,
someone else just random. It's, you know, a dream.
Jacob has a mix and then when you get to Joseph, when you get to the generation after Jacob,
Jacob's sons, Joseph has no direct encounters with God.
It's all dreams and interpreting dreams.
So and you also see a pattern within the patriarchal narratives of escalating sinfulness, right?
Like you think about the things that Jacob's sons get up to, like trying to murder their
brother.
But also what Reuben did and what Simeon did
It would leave on it right you could go down the the list, right?
and
So those are related right there's sort of this decline and so
Because they're not as close to God. God is not as close to them. He still communicates with them though
But now it's by dreams and it's for their sake right like this this thing on God's part is for their sake like as they descend
and further into sin, if God appeared to them directly, they would be responsible for that,
and it would be harmful for them. Yes. So God is, you know, taking a step back, but still talking.
Yes, but still communicating. And so we see that pattern with Joseph, whether we're talking
about Joseph's own dreams early in life, that he unfortunately tells his brothers about,
And they go over like a lead balloon about nice
His brothers and his mom and dad all bowing down in front of him
Or we're talking about the dream any numbers from a certain Andrew Lloyd Webber's show right now, yeah, I'm doing pretty well
Wow, that's good. Thank you fight the show tunes fight the spirit of show tunes
That's what we need to ward off get an exorcist
So you close every door to them take those I love a ways
So
Or then there's the the dreams he interprets for the the cup bearer and the baker right in the prison
That end up helping get him out of prison and then because then he interprets Pharaoh's dream
About the seven lean years and the seven years of plenty
So that right and that's specifically a sort of predictive dream that is given so that
And interpreted by Joseph so that
Not only Joseph can have the status he needs to save his family, but also so that they can store provisions in Egypt can be protected from the famine.
The Egyptians reap the benefits to at that point.
And then the other major that's when we were talking about dreams in the Bible, that was probably the first thing that popped into your head was Joseph, right?
And if a second thing popped into your head, it was probably Daniel.
dreams. There are a lot of deliberate parallels between Joseph and Daniel in
this respect, right? And if you think about in terms of dreams being secondary,
now Daniel does have direct encounters with God in the apocalyptic sections, but
if you think about where the dream and dream interpretation sections, where and
when, those take place in the book of Daniel, those are when he's a young
man like Joseph.
And also when he's in the court of a pagan king and in exile, right?
And so you get his interpretation of Nebuchadnezzar's dream of the statue
made of the different types of metal about the succession of empires.
You get Daniel's own dream about the beasts, which are also about the
succession of empires.
And then the passage that we talked about in a lot of detail in our episode
is one of our Halloween episodes.
I think we're.
we talked about madness, uh, not one step beyond madness, but like, uh, you know, madman,
uh, not like, you know, ad executives in the 1960s, but, you know, the insane, uh, in that
episode, we talked a lot about, uh, Nebuchadnezzar's dream of the tree and how that gets
interpreted and his madness and all of that.
So if you want to deeper dive into that.
that episode is for you. It's still available wherever podcasts are sold. So part of that pattern
of dreams is a secondary communication is that we see a lot of cases where dreams are sent to
Gentiles, right, to be outside of people. So Abimelech, Ferro, Nebuchadnezzar, this continues
use in the new.
Testament. Exhibit A of that is in Matthew 27, verse 19, that's where Pilate, when he's
sitting in judgment of Christ, gets the word from his wife that she had a dream that revealed
to her that she should have nothing to do with condemning that righteous man, right?
So and she was a Gentile at that point. Now, according to the history preserved in
church she laid.
later became a Christian but at that point that wasn't a thing yet, Christ was still standing
in front of her husband.
We also though see dreams being sent to God's people generally that happens when there is
not a prophet, right, directly there and we see an example of that too in the New
New Testament and that's several
of the dreams that Saint Joseph has in Matthew chapters one and two. He has a whole series
of them. So Saint Joseph the betrothed, he has the dream that tells him not to be afraid
to take the Theotokos as his wife because of the the virginal conception. He has the dream
that warns him to go to Egypt. He has the dream that tells him it's time to go back to
from Egypt and he gets the dream on the way that tells him.
to go a different way. And the dream that tells him to not go to Bethlehem but to go
to Galilee to keep away from Herod. So there's this whole series of dreams in which angels
come to him and communicate these things to him. And if you think about it, there's
not a prophet active among the people of that time because St. John the Forerunner
at that time was just an infant, right?
but so that also continues in the New Testament.
And so on the whole, right,
sort of to our overarching themes here,
is that dreams and their interpretation
are deeply connected in Scripture
to the whole prophetic phenomenon, right?
In terms of representing a way
in which God communicates with people
and representing a way in particular communicates
Something
about some danger or something in the future so that it can be avoided or dealt with.
But also, and just as importantly, that not all dreams are dreams in this sense, right?
That a lot of the dreams are, if not most, are what we've been calling internal dreams,
right, that they are just sort of the working out of personal concern.
thoughts fears yeah this kind of this kind of thing so that scripture third
half after this important commercial announcement for 20 meal team borax or
whatever the commercial before which I'm pretty sure it's not going to be borax
but we're gonna talk about we're gonna we're gonna we're gonna leapfrog
Vlog.
Couple...
Oh.
almost 2,000 years forward, about 1,850 years forward, and talk about what happens to the
idea of dreams and dream interpretation in the modern era.
Alright, well that wraps up the second half of this episode of the Lord of the Spirits
podcast on dreams.
We'll be right back.
Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen DeYoung will be back in a moment
to take your calls on the next part of the Lord of Spirits.
Give them a call at 855-
The centuries after the Protestant Reformation brought about a radical reinterpretation of
the epistles of Saint Paul, disconnected from any historical reality.
But Paul operated, during his entire life, as a faithful Pharisee within the Roman Jewish
world.
St. Paul the Pharisee.
Apostle to all nations, Father Stephen DeYoung surveys Paul's life in writings, interpreting
them within the holy tradition of the Orthodox Church.
This survey is followed by DeYoung's interpretive translation of Saint Paul's epistles, which
deliberately avoids overly familiar terminology.
By using words and ideas grounded in first-century Judaism, DeYoung hopes to unsettle commonly
held notions and helped the reader reassess St. Paul in his historical context.
Available now at store.ancientfaith.com.
Again, that is store.ancientfaith.com.
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits,
the Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen DeYoung.
If you have a question, call now at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF radio.
Hey, welcome back everybody. It's the third and final half of this.
I zoned out.
on the commercial, was it for chocolate crusted sugar bombs?
Yeah. Yeah, pretty much. Okay. Okay. Pretty much. Great
cereal. Great cereal. Gives you that sugar that gives you
Vim and Vigor for the whole day.
Yes, yes, we're talking about dreams on this episode of
Laura's spirits podcast. And while we're waiting to see if
we get any calls and actually somebody in the YouTube chat
asked about the distinction between dreams and visions.
Difference between dreams and visions, I mean-
And to me, it's basically like, are you sleeping or are you awake?
Is that or is it kind of hard?
We also we also talked to the first half if you were paying attention, which Father Andrew
clearly wasn't not really.
Yeah, I figured.
I don't blame you.
Right.
I mean, you said yourself at the beginning of the episode, why listen, right?
So I mean, why should you listen?
But the part of it is, is dreams.
In general a person is completely passive whereas within a visionary context. There's more room for interaction
Okay, so I gave the example of st. John in the book of Revelation. No, s I
Know people in the chat are using saying revelations
Well, they're not good people then
Repent tape up you guys repent get your repentance on yeah
the time is short. So, but where you see, for example, say, John asking questions and interacting,
right? Whereas dreams in general tend to be passive. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. All right. We actually do
have a call coming in. So, we have Deacon Constantine calling from St. Paul, Minnesota.
So Deacon Constantine, welcome to the Laura Spears podcast.
Hello, welcome fathers. Thank you for having me.
Yeah, the cities. Yeah, yeah, cities. I love them. Um, I, I want to preface one thing for a certain
thing. Thank you both for your podcast. I'm actually a mental health therapist. And I just want
you to know that your podcast and supportive help people who are going through emotional
struggles and growing both in their emotional lives and their spiritual lives. So I just
want to say thank you for that. Um, I also want to preface and this may be a little spicy
purpose.
that I am, I am a mental health therapist. Yeah. And, uh, uh, I serve as a deacon in
the church and I'm getting my doctorate in Jungian psychology.
So, all right. This is going to be the half for you.
I know, I know it's coming up.
And, but I want, this is why I want to phrase this question is I'm thinking
about the podcast about when you both had, what is the mind? Is it
important to have even today.
2026 an ancient understanding of the mind not a modern one not a
Freudian or Jungian, but what would it mean is important and what would it mean to have
Like an ancient understanding the mind or is that maybe a new question?
Yeah
thoughts or
You know that yeah, we can go from yeah
Well, I mean so we have done and we've talked about that question
Often on a lot and then we had a whole episode called but we have the mind of Christ
You
Yes.
So, you know, one of our big themes has been part of what we're trying to accomplish is
at least to give people a framework for understanding the scriptures particularly.
I mean, this is fundamentally a Bible study podcast, you know, but other ancient texts
and and phenomena whatever to give a framework as much as possible to try
to begin to understand it in a way more like the people who would have received it initially
would have. But the truth, of course, is that we are all modern people, postmodern people.
Yeah. Right. We're all, you know, as, as, what's
the name Charles Taylor basically says, we're all secular now. We can't. What about the
primitive Baptists or they know maybe not the primitive Baptists.
Or the old regular Baptist, I don't know
You know
Whose music is amazing?
We can't flip a switch and and suddenly think you know in a different way and in more in an ancient way
And even if we could like we're embedded in our culture and so the people around us
Would not participate in that and so we would not be able to actually do it the way that they did
Right which involves other people too
So...
We are what we are, you know, but I think that to access to really to appropriate for ourselves more of what's in the scripture and the Holy Church and the church that trying to understand this kind of framework a little bit better can help give us access to more of that kind of thing.
And indeed, I mean, this is the project, this is the project.
to the church fathers who, a significant amount of what they're trying to do is explain the
Bible, which they wouldn't do that if they thought that it was to use the Protestant
term perspicacious, that it just immediately, completely makes sense to anybody who just
picks it up and reads it.
I'm not saying that there's no, there's nothing you can get out of just picking
up and reading the scriptures, no matter who you are, where you are, what your
background is.
Absolutely.
I believe there's a lot that can be drawn.
But the reason why we study it...
and try to listen to it over and over again
and try to understand more deeply,
is because it's not all just immediately available
on the surface in the first read, right?
And so I think that the value in trying
to understand a little bit better
is so that we can appropriate this for ourselves.
Now, I mean, as we've always said, right?
Let's say you've never listened to this show.
Let's say you never have done any of this.
kind of study, or maybe have a completely different, you know, set of context or experience
or you don't speak the language we're speaking in whatever it might be, right? We're not saying
that this is the key that everyone must have to understand the Bible. We're not saying
that by any means. You know, the point is to become faithful. So working on trying
to acquire that framework, you know, it's for not, it's not a goal in the
itself. If the purpose is faithfulness, right? So, you know, if someone just says, this is
just too much for me, I just can't do this. I'm just I am who I am. And that's just the
way that it is. And that person lives a faithful life. Great. You know, thank God that they're
doing it, right? So that's, that's what I think. What do you think, Father?
Yeah, so let me see if I understand the thrust
of your question. Right? Is is what you're you're pushing for a
question of whether, for example, the modern concept of
mental health, right? Yeah, and the mind in that context is
compatible with an ancient understanding of the news. Or
if there's somehow at odds and you have to choose one or the
other is that sort of the rest of what you're asking? Yes.
Because I think that's a real question that yeah, thank you. Right, right. So and I don't I don't know how much currency
his name or thought has in the modern world, but I think of somebody like Jay Adams who back in the
He's in 90s in reform circles
Was doing counseling and just literally denied that mental health was a thing
Okay, sure that mental illness was a thing. He said that's just a secularized version of the idea of spiritual health
right and they were opposed yeah right that's not what I'm arguing for at least
sure no I don't I don't think that's correct yeah and I'm sure I've referred
to on the show to the idea that spiritual health mental health and physical
health are three separable but deeply interrelated things yeah right so I I do
think our concept of mental health is
describing something right and so this is part of part of what we're going to get
into with this certain half that I already alluded to earlier the episode is
that and why I wanted to hammer so much that ancient Near Eastern Pagans
understood that not every dream was divine communication right that a lot of
it was internal processes they didn't have the terms to talk about mental
processes then, right? But it was internal within the person.
right. And so the problem is, and scripture has that category too, as we were talking
about the last half. So having that idea is not the problem. Limiting dreams or limiting
everything to that is the problem. Yeah, right. Cutting off the spiritual end, replacing
the spiritual with just mental. Right. That the spiritual stuff is just all in your
head. Right, effectively.
that's where we run into a problem so I think if you don't have a concept of the
news right then yes you're missing something huge right and frankly you're
not gonna be able to really understand orthodox theology and ways of being and
thinking about the world without a concept of the news but the concept of
the news doesn't sort of evict everything else I mean in that one
Episode
I low-key was plagiarizing Aristotle. I went through Aristotle's five intellectual virtues for people who recognized it, right?
From the Nicomachean Ethics where he has the noose as the pinnacle, right, of what the mind is,
but he also has,
you know, wisdom, prudence, these other reasoning faculties,
right? In another place, he just divides it in two. There's the
epistemonic on and the
the one of which is concerned with the ultimate reality the other one is
concerned with day-to-day you know sort of so yeah so those aren't opposed to each
other yeah to me at all right so I I think it would be it is it is just as
big a mistake for someone in the church to ascribe mental illness or the effect
effects of trauma or something in sort of purely spiritual terms, that's being a faith
healer to me in the same sense as ascribing physical illnesses to spiritual states, right?
The way the people we traditionally call faith healers do.
So yeah, I don't believe in mental health faith healing either.
Yep.
Yeah.
What that I think means that a
practical level is that
As someone who's doing
therapy from an orthodox Christian perspective
Just as any therapist has to also have physiological stuff in mind
As an orthodox Christian therapist you have to have the mental health stuff and the physiological stuff and the spiritual stuff in mind, right?
and
Ideally when there are people struggling with things you have people working together you have a father could
professor, someone involved in therapy, a doctor, right, medical doctor, all working
together with the same goal of health, right, for this person.
Yeah.
Does that help, Deacon?
Yeah, Father, thank you.
That was beautiful.
I would make a quick plug.
I'm on the board of O'Camper, which is the Orthodox Association for Medical Psychological
professionals and our conferences next month. So we strive.
much to these questions and to these points. I'm again it's grateful. Thank you. Thank you so much.
Thanks for calling. All righty. All right. Well, the call board is full. We're going to take
everybody currently on the board and then we're going to move on. So we've got three more.
You're never going to sleep. I know. I know. I know. That's okay. That's okay.
Hey, this is a great side to get a cup all night.
That's right.
I know.
And I didn't even.
sleep that much last night either. We're thinking about almond delight. So we've got
we've got another caller from Minnesota. So we've got Catherine. Catherine, welcome Laura
Spears podcast. Thank you father. Can you hear me? Welcome. Yes, we hear you. Do you
hear us? Okay. Are you not from the city? No, I am from a very sleepy town called Sleepy
population 3,000, very rural here.
from the city, you know, you know, I was gonna say my my mother's people are from a very rural
town in Minnesota called Ogama. Have you ever heard of it? No, is that north? No, no, it's southwest
of the the cities. Yeah, yeah, yeah. Green Isle, Sibley County, I think maybe. Anyway,
That's my neck of the woods, really close, so, okay, well...
I got, I'm not from this part of the state originally.
I'm from more central Minnesota.
So I'm still learning the geography a bit down here.
I hear you.
Okay.
You're in the warm, balmy part of Minnesota now.
Is that, is that what's going on?
Yeah, yeah, the, yeah.
I mean, yeah, pretty much father.
Although like, I can, autumn, you can taste.
Like it's cooler in the mornings and I love that part.
I love autumn and what's coming.
That's changing of the leaves.
Okay, my question is...
Um, before like as I'm tracking like the bridge between that, like what you spoke of in an
ancient Christian understanding of dreams are just like an ancient world understanding
of dreams. And now I feel like we're going to springboard into more of a modern era.
Like someone who came up for me as I was thinking about dreams that was William
Shakespeare and how he treats them.
And like I'm thinking of his big, you know, comedy play, a nice dream where
There's fairies falling in love with men with donkeys heads.
And then, you know, in the tragedy, Romeo and Juliet, like, Queen Mayber, I don't know
if that's the correct pronunciation.
But at one point there's a line where MacRoshio says, I speak of dreams, which are the children
of an idle brain.
And is there like, do you have any thoughts on like, what happens between like the ancient
world and the ancient Christian understanding of dreams and like Freud, I mean, and
like, is Shakespeare there?
I mean, what is he?
Do you have any thoughts on what he's doing with an ancient Christian understanding of
dreams or an ancient, in general, understanding of dreams as he's writing about them and plays?
Does that make sense?
I guess I'm wondering, can he teach us something about that in between?
I feel like, Catherine, I feel like one of my friends must have put you up to this because...
Yeah, this one's all you, Old Man.
I get to talk about Shakespeare
Yeah, I mean this was yeah, this was my deal in undergrad Catherine. I don't know if you know that but
Renaissance drama and poetry was what I spent my a lot of my years. Oh boy 30 some years ago now
Okay, so
How do you boy? How do you how to summarize?
a lot of what's going on in
Shakespeare
But not I mean it's not like he suddenly invents this it's it's you know
it's a progression.
up to him and after him. But a lot of what's going on in
Shakespeare is on some level, the individual is being
invented. Okay. And I once took a graduate level when I was an
undergrad, I wormed my way into a graduate level course, because
I knew the professor let me in. Because I loved I love
studying Shakespeare's plays. And the first play that we
studied was Hamlet. And I think Hamlet is really a key
one.
for trying to get what's going on,
what I'm talking about right now.
And I remember I told my wife about this one time
and she's like, that's insane, why would you do that?
But for me, it was like, wow, this is so great.
Please give me some more.
We spent three weeks talking about the first line
of Hamlet, which of course is, who's there?
And now it wasn't only just those two words.
There was a whole lot of background information
that was being given to take us there.
But, you know, that is, you know, not to put too fine a point on it, but that is the question,
right? I mean, Hamlet later on in that same play as he's contemplating suicide,
he says, you know, basically, to be or to not to be, that is the question. And he's,
he's thinking about ending it all. But the question of who's there is, it is the question of,
of the one in the many, the community of the individual.
You know, yes, something is rotten in the state of Denmark, but something is also rotten
in in Hamlet himself, which is that he, he's not willing to accept that everyone dies, right?
He becomes fixated on his father's death.
And so I think what happens in between the ancient understanding, I mean, this is obviously
just a massive, massive oversimplification.
But I think what happens between the ancient understanding and then what the some of
the stuff that we're about to talk about after we take a couple more callers.
uh, you know, Freud and Jung and whatnot is this kind of invention of the individual. I mean,
we had persons before, of course, but we did not conceive of ourselves as being truly separate.
I mean, think about what's happening in Hamlet. I mean, I assume you know the play that you're
throwing out all these references to Shakespeare, but you know, think about what's happening
happening to Hamlet. He spends the whole play largely talking to himself and when
he does interact with other people. Do they is he really even noticing them? I mean, this
is what messes with Ophelia so much. He's like, what's your problem? We used to be a
thing. And he's like just in his own little world. Yeah. Right. And so yeah. And okay.
And and you know, Midsummer Night's Dream is not the same theme. You brought this
up, right? It's not the same theme. But at the same time, the whole thing is meant
to be, um, like it,
It all gets sort of solved in the end.
It's meant to, it's what, you know, it's what in Shakespeare's genre is a comedy, right?
So comedies always end with weddings in Shakespeare's plays.
That's what makes it a comedy, is it ends with a wedding, you know, and if you're really
good, you get multiple weddings, like as you like it.
I mean, how many there in that?
But what, a lot of what's going on there is essentially saying it was sort of, it
was just all a dream.
You know, fairies are real in that play for sure.
And I was in a production of this when I was in high school, actually, um, and, uh, I'm not going to tell anybody what partly played. But anyway, uh, um, you know, again, it's like, well, it's this kind of spiritual world that exists outside of ourselves is only kind of relevant insofar as it's about us.
Right. I mean, that's what's really, that's one of the things that's going on in that play.
And so there's this reduction.
I mean, actually, Tolkien was
mad at Shakespeare because of what he did to fairies. That fairies became small. And not
literally so in Shakespeare's play, but you may think about the way that we conceive of
fairies here in 2026, is that they're little things. And what does that mean? It means
that we regard spirits as being kind of, yeah, maybe they're out there, not really
that big of a deal. And to me, actually the final
So version of that actually, which I really loved is in labyrinth.
Have you seen that movie labyrinth?
No, I haven't.
Okay.
So at the beginning of labyrinth, and I'm sure a bunch of listeners out there have
heard this, seen this movie, you should watch its great movie from the 80s.
At the beginning of near the beginning of labyrinth, there's a there's a dwarf character
who's going along.
He's going up to fairies who are, you know, tiny little tinkerbell type fairies.
And he's basically got some kind of like, you know.
exterminator juice that he's spraying them with and they fall down and die. He's spraying for
fairies, just like you might spray for ants or whatever. And to me, that's the final version of
that is that they've been completely materialized and turned into nothing special at all. They're
just bugs, right? So I think, you know, what happened in between the ancient, I know this
is kind of a rant now, but you asked what happened between the ancient world and 19th
century and twice it's it's it is
It is the individual, individualism, the individual is kind of invented on some level.
It's not again, not that people didn't conceive of themselves as as distinct, but the individual
has kind of his own little world.
And this is actually, this is the basis for materialism.
Because we start out with a crowded spiritual world, God and the angels and the saints
and the demons and, you know, the heavenly hosts, hosts.
And then, and then with the Reformation, you get, you need kind of shove the saints and the angels off to the side.
And then eventually you get the sense of, okay, that's actually to pay them any attention at all as idolatrous.
So then the spiritual world loses a whole level.
And it's just God and then us.
And then eventually what you get is, it's just us.
And then now here we are, right?
are, right? Post post post modernism, whatever. It's
not even sure there's an us. I'm not even sure there's a me. And that's, I mean, I don't know,
that's my kind of big take on what's wrong with the world. But that's what I think. And I think
Shakespeare is actually a great place to kind of explore some of that stuff. It's, it's, you know,
amazing art, really fun to watch and to read, but also can be
really powerful and, you know, who is there?
So, I don't know.
There you go. Some of the stuff I picked up when I was in undergrad. And I've been thinking
about for 30 years because I love Shakespeare and in some level I've had to kind of justify
why I love Shakespeare so much. And that's one of the reasons, not just that he's entertaining.
He is very entertaining. Yeah. Thank you. I appreciate that. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Wow.
I hardly get a chance to go to rant like that, Father Stephen. So why did you let
Let me go on and on.
Oh, yeah.
So, uh.
Uh, I had a nice little break.
Um, yeah, welcome back spending that much time on who is there.
Seems like writing a whole book on who was the boss, you know, Angela.
According to at least 13 discreet definitions of what it means to be a boss.
Exactly.
Yeah.
Um, anyway, okay.
Well, thanks for calling Catherine.
I hope, uh,
I hope I encouraged you in your love for the Bard of Avon.
Absolutely. That was very, very wonderful. Thank you so much.
And if you find yourself out in, I think there's a little Lutheran church out in the countryside
with a cemetery in Green Isle, go stay a prayer for my ancestors, if you don't mind.
I will. I will. Absolutely, God, I thank you for that.
All righty. All right. Okay, we're going to take another call here.
And I do I would
I will say I do also enjoy those plays that Edward Devere wrote.
You are fired.
At least you didn't say Francis Bacon.
No, that's that's lame.
That's lame.
It's Edward Devere.
Nothing.
You've got to go all the way.
All right.
Okay.
We're going to take another call.
We've got Monica calling from the state of true Yankees, Monica from Connecticut.
I'm Laura Spears-Pud.
good evening. Good evening. Yeah, um, that was a really interesting conversation. I was just like riveted. Um, so now I have
where, where, where, where in Connecticut you from? I'm from the beautiful coastal Milford, uh, which is, uh, really nice this time of
beautiful coastal Milford, uh, which is, uh, really nice this time of year.
I mean, it's like not too hot.
Kind of beautiful.
It was a really good set in Milford.
My dad was from Southington. Do you know where that is?
Yes, I do.
Oh, okay. Very good. Yeah, yeah. Yeah. Actually, you're in another state that another bunch
of my people are all buried in. A lot of them are buried in Marlboro on the other side
of Hartford.
Oh, come visit them and come visit us.
Yeah. I do once in a while. I go pray over my people. So, all right, what's on your
mind?
over my my people so all right what's on your mind
I mean, like listening to all
this and I my question has not
morphed exactly, but it has
more definition now because. I
I'm hearing you guys talk about
basically there's three.
Correct me if I'm wrong, but
there's basically three sources
of dreams, right? First is this
internal source, which you're
saying like modern psychology
has just said that that's the
only source. The second source
The second source would be...
spirit, demons kind of. And then the third is from God. Is this am I kind of getting
the thing here? Yes. Yeah. Okay. Because and so the way that you figure out what discern
what dream is from internally, what dream is maybe from a demonic source because you
were quoting the Bible and it was saying at this, if somebody says the dream and
end up being true and then they use that to try and take you away from God.
God, then that's a demonic dream. Right? I mean, it's okay. Yeah. Yeah. Okay. Yes. Okay.
If somebody, okay, so I'm just like, I've had a lot of crazy dreams to preface this,
but some of the dreams that have actually brought me closer to God ultimately have
actually been like nightmares, but specifically dreams where I'm like fighting demons.
So, so this, and so I'm like thinking, is this like a dream about demons?
Maybe let, maybe God let happen to allow me to kind of like think over some things that
I really needed to, or is this like some Freudian, like do I have to throw all these young Ian
layers on top of it?
Or can it kind of just be like all three kind of coming together?
Because, yeah, I've really had some...
crazy experiences while I've been dreaming. That have ultimately led me closer to God,
led me to refine my faith. And yeah, it's just something that I think about a lot.
Yeah, yeah. I mean, you know, ultimately, the point is what you do with it.
Right.
Right. I mean, I think, I mean, the question of source is an interesting one. But, I
I don't know how most of us would be able to tell exactly, you know, because because dreams
by definition are a little, little ambiguous, you know, right? Yeah, I don't know. I mean,
what do you think, Father? Yeah, well, I mean, all good things come from God, right?
it's definitely and the Bible says that got it good so I think therefore
Any dream
Regardless of the route it takes to get to you
could potentially be
Something that you can see as a gift from God, right? So
We've talked before on the show the reason God allows demons the activity that they're allowed is that he's using that to bring people to repentance
So if you have a nightmare and it brings you to repentance or brings you to an awareness of renewed awareness of God and your need for God
Right, then even though that may have come to you by way of demons. That was ultimately right God's doing God allowed that in order to
Bring about that result like even the stuff so like the example I gave of an internal dream, right?
That's just me going on in my head that eventually
Right by my lack of preparedness
Right will will catch up to me like if I actually did something about that ever
like
That I could say that those dreams were
blessing from God. I don't actually do anything about it because I'm a glutton and a drunkard
and a friend to orthobrosan sinners, but potentially at least I could act on that, right? And you
know, sort of repent of things like procrastination and sloth, you get around to it. Yeah, I have
all the time in the world, right, but so.
these things are ultimately they all can be from God depending on how we receive
them regardless of what route whether they rise up from within ourselves or they
come from it through by way of an angel or a demon ultimately they can all be
from God if we receive them in that way for repentance and faithfulness and
those things
indeed
Does that help Monica? That's helped so much and my second part is sort of to like a very much
follow-up to this is like
What I mean, how do we discern what's appropriate to share with other people?
Especially I'm the wrong person to ask on that
What it comes to those kinds of dreams, because I have had some dreams that I, that were
personally, spiritually, like, like they
I don't know. I don't know. I
don't want to like spurred me to
hire things to be better. And I
do feel like. Like I do want to
share some of that because I
think that there are people
who have maybe had dreams like
that and. But I also don't want
to like. Uh I don't know. I
don't want to like fixate on
anything, and I also don't
And I don't know like
Is this something that I should just like maybe talk to my spiritual father about and
share the dreams with him and then maybe we can like talk about what is what would make
sense like what would be helpful for somebody else who was maybe in my position 10 years
ago to here and what would actually make them fix it on the wrong thing.
Yeah, I mean, I think you have your answer right there.
But I would but I would add to it.
I would add to it.
You know, it really depends on the relationship.
Because someone
you know, if you if you don't know that the person can receive that kind of
conversation in a way that's sober and beneficial, then they're probably not not
ready for it. You know, and also like this can be very personal stuff. So the
relationship needs to be a good close one, you know, within which that kind of
conversation can happen. Because like I said, you know, people can take these
things and weird and, and, and, and, you know,
Father Stevens definition of weird in weird directions
In unhelpful, yes
Right, and so and it you know
There's so much evidence in the Bible about bringing dreams to the community that maybe have community
Significance is my other
It's like I don't know. I'm like sort of
I don't I don't want to do anything spiritually dangerous, but I also maybe
like you're saying like
There are there are certain
dreams that I've had that I know have I don't know that kind of in this conversation that
maybe aren't just for me. Does that make sense? And I'm not trying to be like weird about it.
I'm really, I'm really not trying to be worried about it. I really want to be careful about
it. And so I guess I'm, I guess I'm having like a discernment problem here.
Yeah, I think I mean, part of it is a big piece of it is that stuff that's spent
for a whole community.
question needs to be asked, am I responsible for these people? And if you're not, there's
a good chance that it's not actually for all of them.
But your priest is.
Your priest is, yeah.
And so that's why he can guide you. He knows those other people and he can say, yeah,
I think it would be good if you shared this with whomever or he could think about those
Thank you very much for watching.
other people and say, eh, maybe this one you should, maybe this one's just for you, at least
for now, you know.
Yeah.
Yep.
So all right.
Well, thanks very much for calling Monica.
All right.
We're going to take one more call and then we're going to move on with the last, the
last half.
So we've got Rudy calling from Dallas.
So Rudy, welcome to Laura Spears podcast.
Good evening.
Good.
Awesome. Um, so I just got off work a little bit, uh, ago and I called when I heard and
saw the topic about dreams, uh, and I caught a little bit and I've heard long time listener,
time caller, by the way. My main question kind of was a long monocle.
But my wife is the one that has a lot of
Dreams and how to I guess shepherd that past like
How to intercede and cover my wife
With her dreams
And maybe that's something that from what I'm picking up. Hopefully that's something that
Can kind of glean from the third half a little bit
So, yeah, and then just as for prayers, as for a bless you both from you guys, God bless
you both.
I think, you know, especially when we're talking about particular people in particular relationships
like this, this is definitely a good conversation to have with your own parish priest, your
own father confessor, you know, who can know you, who can know your wife and can, you
You know, gently and...
lovingly give guidance within those particulars yeah yeah so I hope the
third half is helpful yeah see I mean I think I I think the assumption should
always be when God gives you any kind of extra whether a dream or any other
kind of experience spiritual experience when when God gives that to you we
should start out assuming this is just for me yeah yeah and I shouldn't share
with it.
anybody. That should be where you start. It's not necessarily where you end, but that should
be where you start. And then I think at the point where you think, I think it might be
helpful in this situation or that situation to share this with this person or that person.
That's where you bring in another party, right? Whether it's your wife talking to
you, your wife talking to the priest, you talking to the priest, all three of you
being involved, right? You run that by someone else.
else right and sort of their their discernment and spiritualism and see if
they share the same thought right and confirm yeah that would be a good thing
to share or whether they say maybe again but but minimally that's for you
that's a gift that God has given you right and we should start with that
and sort of cherish it as that yeah
Yeah, God bless you both Rudy
Thank you father's appreciate it. You're welcome. You're welcome. All right, well
Skipping over as you said
Five more calls history. No couple thousand years of history with a with a little detour to
You know William Shakespeare there and so anyway
All right, where are we what's going on here in the modern age?
don't even know anymore. Who's there? I don't know. Anyway. Yeah, so when we come to modern
talk about dreams, there's sort of two poles, right? Or two extremes, right? One of those
would be described by folks like Freud, or a fruit dude, or whatever you want to call
at his ilk.
Freud has ilk for sure. But where this is as we've been talking about with some of the collars
and alluded to earlier, where all dreams are just what we've been calling internal dreams. All of
them are just things going on within the person. Right. So there's that poll. The other poll,
which we usually associate with new A.G. cookie stuff is dreams are pure
spiritual, they're all significant, right? And they all have some spiritual significance and connection. And in fact, your dream journal is the foundation of your spiritual life, right? Like, because you're spiritual, but not religious, right? Like, on that side, right? So obviously, neither of those extremes is correct. And then young,
young, uh...
represents a kind of porqué nolostose, but not a porqué nolostose in the sense
that he really draws that back together in the ancient way that we were talking
about or the biblical way, right, where some dreams are total summer spiritual
than this kind of thing, but it's sort of that put through a modernist lens.
That's all for today.
Thank you.
we're going to develop that a little more. But sort of those
two poles, and then young is this kind of weird bridging
figure between them, that sort of the paradigm under which in
this half, we're going to talk about these modern views. So the
word modern is not just there to mean recent, it's meant to
really mean modern. Yeah, late 19th, early 20th century.
period. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Um, so
And and you know
When when our friend the deacon called in I thought he might be this person
I predicted to you when we were talking about this earlier that no matter what we do no matter how hard we try
There's gonna be somebody
And having had a good conversation with the deacon, I don't think he will be this person
But there's gonna be somebody in the YouTube comments on this episode who's gonna go full pedant
about either Freud or young or both, you know, all the nuances we got wrong.
Okay, and part of the reason why I don't think it'll be the deacon is he's actually doing a PhD in this and the guy who
turns into the Earl of Pedantry like never actually has any formal education in the time.
It's always the Google School of Theology.
Yes, it's sub-autodidact, right, who's decided he's an expert.
So all of this framing is the response I'm not going to give to your comment.
But so we'll start with Freud, right?
And so, look guys, I'm not giving a lecture on Freud.
I'm not giving a chorus on Freud.
I'm giving you maybe five minutes on Freud, okay?
Freud's On The Interpretation Of Dreams is like a huge book.
Yeah, I'm not giving you a nuanced take. I'm giving you a very good boat summary
As I'm not claiming to be right giving you an in-depth description, okay, but so here's basically
super short version of how
Freud things dreams work and this sort of sets a trajectory that forms one of the poles as we were saying he's like
I guess one of the
representatives of this. The idea that all dreams are internal dreams. So for him,
every dream springs from some event the day before. It's not always obvious how, right?
There could be a long string of toppled dominoes in between whatever you experienced the day before
and the dream, but there was something that brought that to mind. So there's some trigger,
Right.
for dreams but what that trigger triggers what what detonates when that
trigger goes off is any dream for Freud is an expression of a wish or a desire
for something to be true okay now you may be saying to yourself self I can
see how that would be.
sense if you're having good dreams, right? Like if you dream you're flying. Oh, it's
because you think it would be wonderful to fly or you dream that you're the president
of the United States or the king of the world or something, right? But what about nightmares?
Right? What are things that you wouldn't desire, things that you wouldn't wish for,
right? But that you dream about, right? Or just beyond nightmares, just bad dreams
in general, right? Unpleasant dreams in general. You got to remember for Freud,
There's something called the death drive.
That is that is not
The old hard drive on the last PC I bought before I went back to Mac
But you're a Mac user. I'm a Mac user. I was an early Apple guy and
That I was broke and so I had a PC period
Way back to Mac
I thought you only belong to one religion at a time
That's, well, you know, it's an apple with a bite out of it.
I'm just saying, maybe it's not a different religion.
It's just a heretical form.
Uh, anyway, anyway, uh, that's, um, so the death drive for Freud is, you know, uh, I,
I think one of the best examples of it is, you know, when you're going and you're
looking over a ledge and there's that little thing in the back of your brain that
thinks about jumping? Yeah.
you know, or you're driving over a bridge. Yeah, you know, the
thought crosses your mind to just drive it off of it. I have
that all the time on bridges. And I made the mistake of
telling my wife when she was my fiance about this, why we were
driving across the Bay Bridge in San Francisco. You know, I've
always said the thought when I'm driving. So maybe no
Share every single one of your thoughts.
Yes, that's why I said what the caller said she needed you know, to serve it in what to
share I was like, I'm not the guy, right?
I missed her overshare.
So but right, that kind of thing, but it's also what lies behind all kinds of self-destructive
behavior, right?
You know that cigarettes cause lung cancer, but you keep smoking anyway, right?
me
That, you know, yeah, this was the general you father, the one, one knows that although
the fact that you got defensive there is interesting, psychologically, but the you are in like the
tobacco capital of the world, but I literally drive by just fields and fields and fields
of tobacco every day.
It's true.
But so all of all of those patterns, right?
So Freud, of course, doesn't have a cut.
concept of sin, right, or anything like this. But he has this, there is within this drive
toward destruction, right, that is a thing, right, that that is active in us. And so some
of those dreams could be an expression of that, the wishes or desires associated with
that, right. And so that's how he could say all these dreams are expression of that
wish or desire. But then there is also something in dreams that Freud calls dislocated.
Right? Meaning, even when you're dreaming, dreaming for Freud is not purely just your
subconscious mind running wild. Your conscious, at least part of your conscious mind is still
in action. That's why someone could learn how to lucid dream is because there is some
element of your rational faculties. Right? When you're dreaming, you could probably
I think of examples of dreams.
you've had in which you think about things or try to act rationally with
something that's happening, even if it's completely irrational and weird, right?
Um, so there is some element and for Freud, part of what that still remaining
rational faculty does is sort of censor, uh, the dream, censor those
subconscious desires, right?
It has to do with all
to look at some of those subconscious desires that are now coming to the fore in your dream
and go, right? So it'll sort of, you know, warp them a little bit to make them a little
more palatable, right? Yeah. And that forms a kind of suppression, right? So this normally
subconscious desire triggered by something that happens during the day, expresses itself.
Uh, to your mind in a dream, but your conscious mind kind of holds it back and sensors it.
So for Freud, when it went, when a psychoanalyst, right, the analyst is dealing with a client
or a patient and is interpreting their dreams.
The goal then is to bring out that latent censored content, right?
to be like, Oh, right, you're, you're the, the
location changed this into that right so it turned you know the knife into a
balloon right or whatever right I'm deliberately not using any of the sexual
examples that spring to mind in Freud because I'm trying to be fair to Freud
and Freud during his life was accused of making everything about sex and he
He got really grumpy about that.
insisted he did not do that that sexual the sex drive was obviously the drive to
reproduce is obviously a powerful drive within humans but there are others
according to Freud so I don't want to pigeonhole it with that using the
sexual examples but they probably spring to mind for you too and are
probably best unsaid on ancient faith radios airwaves so you can fill in
those blanks but you can see how within that again it's just all
internal process.
It's just sort of your mind trying to work things out that are going on in your mind at
a subconscious or unconscious level, but that are now coming to the fore in dreams and you're
working them out.
And even a lot of, I mean a lot of people, a lot of people in psychology who are into
Freud specifically who would disagree with a lot of Freud's particular claims and conclusions
will still, in general, tell you something like, well, dreams are your mind working.
out stuff from the day before, right? Or working through things, you know, that worries, cares,
desires, right? Like that, you can see that kind of general. That's why I say he represents
one pole where everything is an internal process. All dreams are internal dreams.
They're just all going on within you and your own mind. Okay. So now young. Okay. And here
Here we're talking about you.
himself not everyone who's a young Ian not everyone who studies young young not
everyone who appreciates young because they do all kinds of things with them
they take all kinds of insights from him and take them in different directions
right so we're not saying anybody who's a young Ian or anyone who has ever
quoted young publicly believes everything we're about to say we're
just talking about the man the historical person Carl Jung this is
what he seemed to understand. And once again, like with Freud.
This is a very, very short summary. So there's lots of depth here that we're not going into,
lots of nuance that we're not going into. But so similar to Freud, there are things in dreams
that are being communicated to the conscious mind, being brought to the conscious mind
from the unconscious, but you have to remember that freak Yung
There is the collective unconscious
Lots of Jungians mean lots of different things by that now, okay, but
We're gonna talk about again Jung himself
So be the collective unconscious means that for young
The unconscious might you don't have your own individual unconscious mind
The unconscious mind is something that's shared
By for Jung essentially all of humanity at any given point. Yeah, it's a sort of
Collective thing that we can all tap into right and so dreams that are communication
But that communication is not coming from spirits or God
Right that communication is coming from the collective unconscious to your consciousness
So, all dreams are sort of this collective unconscious mind communicating to your personal
conscious mind.
And that's why, so because of that, because all of this communication is coming from this
collective unconscious mind, that's why Jung believed you could identify these universal
symbols.
and patterns that represent and mean the same thing in everyone's dreams, right?
Because it's what this one collective unconscious communicating to your consciousness.
So it speaks the same language essentially to everybody.
Yeah, it's a language of patterns and symbols.
Thank you very much.
So, in order to understand dreams, you with your conscious mind have to learn that language.
You have to identify those patterns and those symbols.
And now, again, this is the part where people get grumpy.
So when I talked about Jung's Gnostic cult and stuff people got grumpy at me
But again, we're just talking about Jung the person here.
This doesn't mean every Jungian totally believes this.
So Jung's probably most famous or infamous work is his red book.
And that emerges out of a series of personal experiences he had, which, and again, I know
there's lots of new ones here, but the broad strokes is he had what he believed to be
during World War One he
had what he believed to be a powerful experience of the collective unconscious, where like he
tapped into it, right, due to the sort of collective trauma that was going on in Europe.
And that experience led him to sort of become a hermit, right, he sort of locked himself
pup, right? And again, from his perspective, allowed himself to slip
too madness, which for him was something like letting go of his own personal conscious rational
mind and sort of just submerging himself into the collective unconscious to try to learn
and understand from it.
That's sort of his understanding of what was going on.
And so, the red book is so...
of his dream journal the dreams experiences and hallucinations that he had during that period
of sort of self-allowed madness and so the red book is not just like
him writing prose text there's drawings right of dragons and stuff there's all kinds of stuff in
there right um but that's because that's what it was and then after a period of time doing that
that he sort of got himself together.
So, it's important that young, when we're talking about the collective unconscious, people are
very quick to run with that in a new age direction, that was the collective unconscious God, right?
Is it something, and young insisted it was not supernatural, and you might think how
How can that be?
Well, Jung, again.
Carl Jung the person, not everyone who identifies as a Jungian, but Carl Jung the person believed
in telepathy. He believed that literally every human, all human minds were connected to each
other telepathically. And that's what produced the collective, or that's what the collective
unconscious was. It was that level of where everyone is minds are connected to each other.
You may say.
Well, telepathy sounds supernatural to me.
Well, now Jung is a, is a 19th and early 20th century German.
So everything's vision shaft.
You gotta remember right over him.
No telepathy was a scientific reality.
He believed it was going to be measurable and observable and
all of those things.
It's just that science hadn't reached the point where it
could quantify and study it.
Yeah.
I mean, it's like, it's like betazoids starchy.
Yes.
Right.
So at
that's important, right? Because we've got to be fair to him, right? And so, and this is important
for understanding his relationship to Gnosticism and not just Gnosticism, right? Before the Nagamadi
Library was discovered, the largest collection of Gnostic texts we had was called the Jung Codex,
because he compiled it. But he was not just interested in Gnosticism. He was also interested
in hermiticism as a whole.
He was interested in alchemy and wrote about it.
Um, but it's not that he believed in those things in the ancient or medieval senses.
It's that he, he looked at those things sort of the way of various looked at Islam, right?
So if you don't know about a very is the very is looked at Islam is basically philosophy
for dummies.
So he's a Muslim living in a Muslim country.
But he believed.
Okay, look.
that fundamentally the Islamic religion for a veroese was trying to teach people who are not capable of understanding
philosophy and for him that was specifically Aristotle's philosophy. They weren't equipped to understand it.
Well, we'll communicate the basic truths and the basic ethics of these kind of things to people.
And we're just going to say God told it to mom.
So it's like, it's like, you know, these people that look at
religions or, you know, various kinds of
initiatory practices of the pre-modern world
and try to come up with scientific
ways of justifying them, like, oh, well,
they were doing this and this, but it had this effect,
this material effect, which they didn't know about,
but they were able to manipulate it appropriately because of the things that they were doing.
You know, right? Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. And so Carl Jung being a
German of his era, right, believed that he was now that
these ancient people and medieval people were on to
things regarding the collective unconscious regarding all the
things that he was writing about. But they being more
primitive, et cetera, et cetera, we're writing about them in
these sort of religious and supernatural and weird ways
because they didn't really understand them. But now he
was scientifically describing them. Yeah, yeah, right. And so
his scientific expertise.
was, of course, the reality that they were all gesturing at. And so that's why he was interested
in them, right? He saw them as earlier primitive understandings of the same kind of phenomena
he was dealing with, right? So you could see, well, on one hand, right? And of course,
he's denying anything supernatural. But on one hand, he doesn't have like Freud ultimately
dreams are just something happening inside a closed box, right?
the box is open and stuff is coming into and out of the box from outside the box
from other boxes right sort of other nodes on the on the neural net right but
it's still not communication from an agentic being a being with agency other
than yourself right right it wasn't that it wasn't that another huge
was telepathically sending thoughts to you even. It was that there's this layer of consciousness
below the primary layer at which all the minds are connected. Yeah. Right. But they all together
form kind of a hive mind, an unconscious hive mind. Yeah. Right. It wasn't like.
And so it's still...
while it's distinguishable from Freud, very clearly in various ways, it's still within the
category of everything is ultimately an internal process, at least internal to humans,
to humanity as such. So then we get to the other pole, right, that we talked about,
that being the kind of new-agey view of dreams and dream interpretation.
And of course, when we get into this, it gets a whole lot more nebulous, right?
Because it's not like there's a systematic theology of new age movements.
Right.
And when we talk about new age, like the new age, I don't know if they still have
new age sections at bookstores, but in the late 80s and into the 90s, there was
a new age section at the bookstore.
And that included everything from like Wiccan stuff to like UFO cults.
Oh, yeah.
That crystals and everything it was
just all this stuff thrown into a big bucket, right? Um, so, you know, how, how do we even
talk about that? So I have kind of chosen a representative book, right? Uh, and I've
chosen it just based on popularity and sales and the fact that it's directly related to
dreams and that this is not a recommendation or an endorsement, obviously, but I'm using
as an example here.
of sort of the core ideas at work here. Llewellyn's complete dictionary of dreams. Okay, okay,
which was compiled and edited by a guy whose name is not Llewellyn. Oh, which is also strange.
Yeah, right. So maybe he channeled Llewellyn who knows. But that's, but so this is, this
This is, again, a very po-
popular, well-known in New Age circles, guide to dream interpretation.
And so this represents a good sort of general example of the kind of ideas you're dealing
with in the New Age interpretation or understanding of dreams.
Llewellyn is the name of the publisher, by the way.
So that's...
Oh, there you go.
That's where it comes from.
Okay.
Yeah.
Why do I not know the name of New Age publishing houses?
I don't know.
Steven, this is a-
massive lacuna in your knowledge. Yes. Yes. And I have zero
desire to go to Sedona and try and figure it out. I've been to
Sedona and you know, can confirm. Can confirm. I have I have
to I have an ad who got married in Sedona. Not a weird new age
thing. But yeah, yeah, happened to be very pretty area for
sure. Very pretty. But and I do have to say that particular
wedding cake.
uh, was like 85% brandy and all us kids fell asleep in the car on the way home.
Um, but anyway, uh, that's, um, and so basically, so the idea is within this is
that, uh, uh, dreams are a communication to your conscious mind again.
but from your higher self
Not yourself who has gotten high
But I could see why you would make that mistake
given the subject matter
But from your higher self meaning and this higher self is associated with the divine so essentially the self is divine
You're God the basic new agey thing
right, but
It's also higher this isn't this is you in
the future. This is like you 2.0, right? The divine you that you're the butterfly that
you're going to blossom into at the end of all this. Communicating back to you primitive
material you in the present day to help guide you toward itself. Okay. This is like that
old sitcom second chance.
Alex Rocco went into the past to try to teach his younger self a young Matthew Perry get
him on the right track and not make the same mistakes. That is the most obscure reference
I've made. Oh, probably on this show. But I'm not going to go any further with it. Okay,
I want to. I really want to. But I'm back.
So
So you have this divine self that you're teleologically oriented toward you're becoming this divine
you but divine you in the future is sending these messages back to you to help guide you
to become that in your dreams.
And so then interpreting the dreams is interpreting what is the guidance you're getting from
Thank you for watching!
this higher self. And so like in this dictionary, it's just piles of symbology, right? This represents
that. This color represents that, right? This article of clothing represents that. But it's
just taken from all over the place. So there's stuff they've taken out of Jung, but there's
There's also stuff they've taken out of like ancient pagan stuff, stuff they've
taken out of medieval stuff, stuff that who knows where they got it that some guy made
up.
Right?
You know, just stuff, right?
All just sort of piled together, right?
And I'm sure, again, that's that's one book.
I'm sure if you've got a different book, maybe even from the same press, same new
age press, there'd be all different stuff, right, for the same symbols and everything,
right?
Because again, there's not like a system.
theology of New Age. But so that gives you at least an idea of the kind of
approach you find to dreams in a New Age context. Well, what do these, again, what
do all of these sort of modern approaches have in common? It's that for them all
dreams are dreams, right? That it's all the same thing, right? And it all
all exists purely on sort of the human
plane, and God or angels, demons, pagan gods, all of that stuff is really out of the picture
because if you have dreams with any of those things in them, they're just representing something.
Some part of yourself, some part of your higher self, some sublimated desire, some symbol
from the or pattern from the collective unconscious, but they're not an act.
being outside of you communicating with you. That's what they're not, right? The
reality of the spiritual world is out of the picture, right? The spiritual world
gets reduced to sort of mental processes of one kind or another, right? And you
know the New Age will say it's spiritual, but it's a very loose use of the
word, spiritual, right?
But the problem is, with all these approaches then, based on those commonalities, is that
all of those set human beings up for deception, right?
All of those set you up to misinterpret what's going on in your dreams, right?
All of those ascribe whatever it is to at best, this is just
working out of some primal desires you have that you're suppressing, at worst this is communication
from your higher self that you should follow this advice because it's all leading you in a
good direction, right, when interpreted correctly and leading you to make all kinds of bad choices,
right? And if you think a demon doesn't know the contents of a book you're reading and
can't throw you a dream to tell you to do all kinds of kooky stuff if you're reading
being Llewellyns.
complete dictionary of dreams. I don't know who you're kidding, right? Like that, right?
That's easy, right? And so this is very early on in this show. I'm talking first few episodes.
We talked about this, that that knowledge of the material world, the technological
knowledge that we've gained in the modern age is real. We can make microwaves, right?
Michael
Cars are nice, and cars are nice, plane travel is nice, satellites are cool, all this stuff
is real learning and real advancement and has some value, like you're listening to
this on the internet.
So that's all well and good, we're not saying that's bad, we're not saying we need to
We all become, you know, ancient people.
and go back to living the way they lived in 3000 BC, right? Or 2000 or 1000 or even the
first century AD. But there was a trade off that was made. And it wasn't made sort of
consciously by any given person, but it was a trade off that was made by societies and
cultures to pursue that knowledge of the material world and the physical world whole
right which produced all these advancements while neglecting the spiritual wisdom and spiritual knowledge that had been present in the ancient world.
And so this is an area in terms of understanding dreams in which humanity is not only not progressed since the ancient world but is actually kind of regressed.
Hmm
That modern people are actually less savvy about these kind of things than ancient people were
Even though we're much more savvy about technological things and things about the material world
right and so
The goal of what we do on this show and what the goal should be for all of us is people is again not to
Retreat to try and become an exit as if that were possible
right, but to
reacquire the spiritual wisdom
To go with
with and to guide our sort of material science and understanding and knowledge, right? It's
not that one is good and one is bad. It's that one can run a muck if you don't have
the other. And the other, the spiritual wisdom, right, the knowledge of God, right, is far
more important than the other.
down.
Well, here we are at the end of the third half. We actually just had someone in the in the YouTube chat say yeah, could you guys wrap this up?
I've got things I got to do
Well, we're wrapping it up friend
You know, I
This is this very much fits into the kind of a genre and this is probably why AI suggested we should do this
Father's he said at the beginning this definitely fits into the genre of
of a kind of show that we do, which is we talk about something that a lot of people consider
to be kind of out there. And we make the point of, okay, it's not actually out there, it's
in here. And also, what do you do about all this? Well, you don't go crazy. You don't
decide, oh, I've got some kind of special revelation that's going to take me in a
a new direction and everybody else.
that no one's ever heard of before. You know, one of the things that we saw in the scriptures that we looked at was
God warning the people of Israel
that if prophets tell them stuff that's
You know saying that saying they're having dreams
And that the conclusion is that they should go do something other than what God commanded them to do
God says not only don't listen to those prophets, but even you know
video.
The Death-
penalty is aimed at them. Of course, in our time, we actually have something worse than
the death penalty within the church, and that's excommunication. And I think that, you know,
as you said, Father, the kind of spiritual wisdom that has been neglected in favor of
the material wisdom that we now have.
has, you know, opened us up to the possibility of being deceived because we don't know quite
how to recognize spiritual experiences in the best possible way.
And this connects with the question that the deacon was asking too, like, what's the,
you know, is it necessary, is it good, is it required to try to acquire, to, you
know, to reappropriate some of this wisdom?
And I think it's definitely good.
But we're not, you know, utterly lost with without it. We are where we are, you know
But what we can do is
receive one of the most basic pieces of wisdom about spiritual experiences, whether it's dreams or visions or
Miracles, you know, that you see or whatever it might be and that is that restraint and caution are the normal
posture, right
We're so used to thinking and functioning in a materialist way that when we see something
that's that is outside of those boundaries, we might potentially think that we're special.
We might think I have something I need to give the whole world here that they all need this
from me. But but that is quite often can be deception, deception for yourself.
maybe for other people. A number of the stories from the Holy Fathers are about a monk seeing
what presents as an angel and saying, you know, get out. And the conclusion always is it's
better to tell an angel to get out than to unwittingly receive a demon because you're
deceived and you don't know how to discern what's true and what's not and what the
true reality of things is.
So I think that number one that caution is really an important
Yeah posture I think is the best way to describe it. It's the appropriate posture is caution restraint
To embrace the ordinary life
Right, but also, you know, if there's one message we're trying to convey with all this too is that
look that the spiritual experiences actually are normal and
Maybe coming back to the point where we have some
wisdom about these things, we're going to have to accept that they're normal again. That
doesn't mean we need to go crazy about them, but that if we live as ordinary people and
live with the ordinary faithfulness that Christ has given us and that the saints have demonstrated
for us, that that will place us in a position where we will have more discernment. You
know, the saints that are able to test the spirits and to occasionally do battle
with e
spirits are saints that did the ordinary every day, sometimes very boring and difficult repetitive
practices of faithfulness that are the norm of Christian life, prayer, fasting, almsgiving,
these basic things, these foundational things, these required things. It turns out that it's
Once again, surprise, surprise, all about repentance.
And...
The irony of the modern age is that in thinking that they could come up with a scientific explanation of a lot of these things
Actually set us up not for greater knowledge, but for less knowledge
for less knowledge, it's an irony
you know knowledge isn't always just increasing sometimes it's getting lost and
Sometimes it's something that we shouldn't have forgotten that we need it and to me
One of the beautiful things about having this particular conversation is that again it opens
up parts of the scripture that maybe sometimes we kind of don't know what to do with or just
sort of read past and don't really absorb it because we don't have a framework to absorb it
and so God willing you know with this conversation we've extended the framework just a little bit
so that as you read the whole of the scriptures that more and more of it can
lead you on to that faithfulness that Christ calls all of us to.
So I'm, I'm grateful for this one. Thank you.
So, uh, one song that involves dreams that I'm not going to be quoting at the end of the episode
is California Dreaming.
And, uh, as many of you listeners know, I grew up in Southern California.
And, uh, so did my
wife, my wife is from Orange County. And you know, every so often somebody asks us, hey,
do you ever want to go back to California? We all immediately say no. Because, you know,
I don't have to list all the issues with California currently. But that doesn't mean
I'm sort of immune to the pull of...
You know the place the place I come from and
Last night I was watching a
Live musical performance from that just happened to be the place where I grew up and I was thinking about
So there was this place out in Ventura Ventura is sort of like Northwest of of Los Angeles
And I first went out there because I had a friend who lived in Thousand Oaks, which is sort of on the way out there and
There was a an amazing comic book store in Ventura called Ralph's comic book corner
and this was back of the day when
They weren't like reprinting tons of old comics like they do now for old nostalgic guys like me if
You wanted to like read the stories and see the art
from the
classic stories back in the 50s and 60s you had to go track it down one issue at a time somewhere
out in the in the world and Ralph Scott McCord was like a gold mine for that but a couple blocks away
there was this cafe and if you could get out there it was a drive but if you could get out
there in the morning or even lunchtime that was hard to do because you had to go through the
101-110 interchange, which is a nightmare if you've ever been to LA, but if you could get out there at that time
This cafe had the most amazing blueberry pancakes
You could ever have in your life. I mean fresh whole blueberries
pancake batter made from scratch
fresh brewed coffee
You could go and sit
They had outdoor seating you could go and sit out there and Ventura is near the coast so you'd smell the
the ocean breeze, the salt air, eat those pancakes, drink that coffee. It's amazing. And I was
thinking, man, what I wouldn't give to go back one more time and eat those pancakes and
go dig for gold in the stacks at Ralph's. But Ralph's comic corner shut down a few
years ago. That cafe is close to and one of the evidence is that you're an old
guy like me.
is that your dreams start being of the past. Your dreams start being about
trying to recapture those kind of beautiful moments in the past that you
remember and the joy you had. You want to go back and you want to recover it. When
you're a young person, which I used to be once, your dreams are all in the
future. It's all these joys you imagine in the future when you
meet that person and fall in love and get married and have kids and all the
thing you know you achieve what you want to achieve in your career and you have
all those things that they're out in the future but what both of those have in
common regardless of whether you've crossed the Rubicon into dreaming about
the past instead of the future now is that none of them are in the present
none of them are a
aimed at finding the joys and the beauty and the good things that God has placed in my life
right now today. They are aimed at a past that will never come again or a future that
may never come to be, rather than the beauty of today, what God is doing.
how he's revealing himself, what he's communicating to me today.
So you can go tonight onto social media and quote Father Stephen DeYoung is saying,
give up on your dreams, whether it's the past or the future.
Let it go, right?
Live today. There is so much good and so many blessings.
Available to you right now today
If you're willing to stop and see them and take advantage of them and so that's what I wanted to say at the end of this episode
Give up on your dreams because this is the day that the Lord has made
So let us rejoice and be glad in it
Amen, amen. Well, that's our show for tonight. Thank you for listening everybody a few
happen to get through to us live and give us a call. We'd still like to hear from you.
You can send us an email lordofspiritsnationfaith.com. You can message us at our Facebook page.
You can also leave us a voicemail at speakpipe.com slash lordofspirits.
And if you have basic questions about Orthodox Christianity or you need help finding a parish,
go to orthodoxintro.org. And join us for our live broadcasts on the
second and fourth Thursdays of the month at 6 p.m. Eastern 3 p.m. Pacific.
A candy-colored clown they call the Sandman, tiptoes...
my room every night.
You've been listening to the Lord of Spirits, with Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew Steven Damick, and Father Steven DeYoung, a listener-supported presentation of ancient faith radio.
And I beheld, and I heard the voice of many angels round about the throne, and the beasts, and the elders.
And the number of them was ten thousand times ten thousand, and thousands of thousands, saying with a loud voice, worthy as the land that was...
slain to receive power and riches and wisdom and strength and honor and glory and blessing.